<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The epistle congratulatorie of Lysimachus Nicanor of the Societie of Jesu, to the Covenanters in Scotland. VVherin is paralleled our sweet harmony and correspondency in divers materiall points of doctrine and practice.</title>
            <author>Nicanor, Lysimachus, 1603-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E203_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17894</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860295</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860295</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73761)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 36:E203[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The epistle congratulatorie of Lysimachus Nicanor of the Societie of Jesu, to the Covenanters in Scotland. VVherin is paralleled our sweet harmony and correspondency in divers materiall points of doctrine and practice.</title>
                  <author>Nicanor, Lysimachus, 1603-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Young and Richard Badger],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini M.DC.XL. [1640]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Lysimachus Nicanor is a pseudonym of John Corbet.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>In this edition E3r line 2 has: Lawes,.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Covenanters --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112413:1"/>
            <p>THE EPISTLE CONGRATULATORIE OF Lyſimachus Nicanor <hi>Of the Societie of JESU,</hi> TO THE COVENANTERS IN SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>VVherin is paralleled our ſweet Harmony and correſpondency in divers materiall points of Doctrine and Practice.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JUDG. V. XXIII.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Curſe ye Meroz (ſaid the Angel of the Lord) curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof: becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the Mightie.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JER. I. X.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>See, I have this day ſet thee over the Nations, and over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, to root out, and to pull down, and to deſtroy, and to throw downe, to build, and to plant.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Anno Domini M.DC.XL.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112413:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112413:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LYSIMACHUS NICANOR</hi> of the Societie of JESU, TO THE COVENANTERS IN SCOTLAND, <hi>Wiſheth full Union and Peace with us.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe heartily congratulare with you <hi>(moſt worthy Brethren of the holy League)</hi> and alſo rejoyce in behalfe of our Mother-Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun returne from your former errors and hereſies. This puts us in expectation, that ſhortly your return ſhall be full: for ſeeing in ſo ſhort time, and with ſo good ſucceſſe, you have forſaken the former erroneous Doctrine of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> concerning the <hi>Civill Magiſtrate,</hi> and have happily joyned with us, you wil alſo betimes abjure all that yet remaineth. You have ſo well begun at the <hi>Head,</hi> the <hi>Civill Magiſtrate,</hi> that wee truſt you ſhall embrace the remanent members of our doctrine with a continued ſucceſſe, whereof you may juſtly glory.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quod fortuna ratum faciat quis dicere falſum</l>
               <l>Audeat, &amp; tantae ſuffragia vincere ſortis?</l>
            </q>
            <p>I remember the ſaluation that was given to the Scots Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector (who is now our holy Father <hi>Pope Urbanus</hi>) about the time of his inauguration and conſecration to be Pope, <hi>Salve Protector Scotorum,</hi> and of his anſwer, <hi>Agnoſco nomen &amp; omen:</hi> And now hee is more ready to protect you then ever hee was, ſince you draw ſo neere unto him. And yet at your laſt defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to your King againe at the Camp, wee feared your revolt to your rejected Proteſtant doctrine: but this your laſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, wherein you recollect your ſtrength,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Julii,</hi> 1639.</note> puts us in hope that you will not returne to your vomit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112413:3"/>
And albeit the Anticovenanters thinke you ſo neere the height of impiety, that they ſay,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nil erit ulterius quod veſtris moribus addat</l>
               <l>Poſteritas.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Yet we thinke it is praiſe worthy that you are come to ſuch degrees of perfection, that your poſterity ſhall be ſo farre from out-ſtripping you, that they, imitating you, ſhall take you for their pattern. To them it ſhall be ſufficient glory (ſeeing they cannot go beyond you) to doe the ſame things which you have done: <hi>eadem capient facient<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> minores.</hi> And therefore you do moſt prudently in your <hi>Proteſtations</hi> defend your Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>without</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> Authority, leſt acknowledging a fault herein, you ſhould defraud your poſterity of the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; or to uſe your owne words,<note place="margin">Proteſtat. in Sept. 1638. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>You ſhould precondemne alſo the like laudable courſe in the like neceſsity to be taken by the Poſterity.</hi> And therefore it is your wiſdome to ſtand to the juſtification of all your proceedings, and to refuſe an Act of <hi>Oblivion,</hi> and accept of no leſſe then an Act of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> It is ſo farre from being a fault which you have done, in taking the Kings Caſtles, and thruſting out his other ſubjects out of their houſes, with your other actions, that it is rather a <hi>merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious work;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proteſt. 18. Decemb. 1638</note> and therefore you ſay well, <hi>We deſerve and expect approbation and thanks from his Majeſty in his own due time, for keeping his evill Counſellers and bad Patriots from put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hand in his best ſubjects.</hi> And in your laſt Petition to his Majeſty after your Aſſembly, to deſire your King to approve of your proceedings, you ſay, that <hi>you are aſſured of his juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your actions, and that you are afraid you ſhould bee thought to have offended in nothing ſo much as in Lenity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Anticovenanters</hi> are no more offended with your writ &amp; printed Books, (which they call infamous Libells, and Jeſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Paſquils) then they doe pleaſe us, not that wee delight in your contention; as the <hi>Vultur</hi> in the Apologie beheld the ſtrife of the <hi>Lion</hi> &amp; the <hi>Bore,</hi> to ſnatch the prey from both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but with an aſſured hope that within ſhort time you ſhall become our <hi>fratres fraterrimi,</hi> for your writings &amp; actions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe no leſs; as being moſt conducible for our ends, &amp; grounded upon our arguments. You ſhall do us no ſmall pleaſure, if you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112413:3"/>will cauſe to be drawn up ſuch heads of Doctrine, wherin we do now of late agree, that ſetting thoſe apart, as <hi>not controverted,</hi> wee may conferre with you in that wherein as yet wee <hi>differ:</hi> and in the mean time, as by your diligent peruſall of our books, our ſtrong reaſons have prevailed with you; ſo I pray you be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in reading of them: which I hope ſhall produce the like effect in that which remaineth. For a preparative to this work, I will thankfully remember (ſo farre as my weak memory will ſerve) ſome points, which by hearing and reading your papers, I find firſt to be <hi>ours,</hi> and from us wiſely received by <hi>you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, your diſlike of <hi>Monarchical government</hi> doth pleaſe us very well; for wee diſlike it ſo much, that (to ſpeak this under the Roſe) we cannot ſimply grant it to the Pope himſelfe, but with ſuch reſtrictions and limitations, that what we grant him now, we may take it from him the next day to our ſelves, as I might inſtance in many particulars; but eſpecially in his <hi>infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility</hi> and <hi>temporall power;</hi> which we give him with ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions &amp; limitations (if you will conſider our books) that we intend for <hi>our ſelves,</hi> that which we give him. But more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, we agree with you in contemning the <hi>Monarchicall government</hi> of the <hi>civill Magiſtrate:</hi> for as wee ſay by that great pillar of our Church, Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Billa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de Rom. Pont. li. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Haec guberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio id requirit, ut ſit quidam in republica ſummus aliquis Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps qui &amp; omnibus imperet, &amp; nulli ſubjiciatur,</hi> that is, This government requireth this, that there ſhould be indeed in the republick ſome Prince that is Supreme, both to command all, &amp; be ſubject to none. For this government hath this great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, that when the Prince doth wrong his ſubjects (as you proteſt your King doth you) there is no remedy but <hi>patience;</hi> for why, all the Judges under him are but his <hi>Deputies,</hi> and all the power &amp; authority they have of the <hi>Sword,</hi> is the <hi>Kings,</hi> &amp; it can never ſtand with ſenſe or reaſon, that his Majeſties <hi>owne Power</hi> &amp; <hi>Authority</hi> can be uſed againſt <hi>Himſelfe.</hi> And hence it is, that Princes being <hi>Legiſlators,</hi> are above their Lawes, &amp; may diſpence with them as they think expedient. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſayes the Prince of the Schoolmen, <hi>Princeps non obligatur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nis legibus, quia nemo ſibi imperat, &amp; ſibi ipſi lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imponit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. quaeſt</hi> 93. a. 5.</note> 
               <hi>A Prince is not bound to his own laws, becauſe no man doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112413:4"/>himſelf, or impoſe a Law on himſelfe.</hi> Though this ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſtrange to ignorant men, yet it is moſt true, and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it well, for its grounded upon good reaſon: for the Law is given by a <hi>Superior</hi> to an <hi>Inferior,</hi> and no man can be <hi>inferior</hi> to himſelfe, and ſo can give no Law to himſelf; and ſince he can give no Law to himſelfe, none of his Lawes can oblige him.</p>
            <p>But what? ſhall he be an <hi>Exlex,</hi> a lawleſſe man then? I anſwer with the Schoolmen in two Aphoriſmes. I. <hi>Princeps non poteſt ſervare legem ſuam ex affectu obedientiae, quia nullum agno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcit Superiorem in republica: ſed tantum ex affectu illius virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, in cujus materia collocatur id quod lege ſtatutum eſt:</hi> The Prince cannot keep his owne Law, out of the affection of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, becauſe he acknowledgeth none in the republike to be Superior to him: But only he can keep his Law, out of the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he hath to that vertue, in the matter wherof, that which is ordained by Law, is placed. II. Aphoriſme. <hi>Princeps tenetur quoadvim directivam, non quoad coactivam, ac proinde tam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tſi peccet contra ſuam legem, non tamen fit reus poenae per legem impoſitae quia nemo poteſt legitimè puniri niſi à Superiori.</hi> The Prince is bound to his Lawes in ſo far as they have a vertue to direct him, but not as they have any coactive power. And therefore albeit he tranſgreſſe his Lawes, yet hee doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty of the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of the Law, becauſe no man can be puniſhed lawfully, but by his <hi>Superior.</hi> For this cauſe, that ſaying of <hi>Cyrillus</hi> is remarkable. <hi>Nemo leges regum impunè re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probat, niſi reges ipſi; in quibus pravaricationis crimen locum non habet. Prudenter enim dictum eſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> impium eſſe, qui dixerit regi, Iniquè agis.</hi> No man can reject the Laws of Kings without puniſhment, but Kings themſelves, in whom the crime of their tranſgreſſion hath no place:<note place="margin">Thom. loc. cit. Suar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>35.</hi> Laym. in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lib. <hi>1.</hi> De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th. cap. <hi>9.</hi> Decan. cap. <hi>6.</hi> de legel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ana. quaeſt. <hi>12.</hi> Syl. cit. quaeſt. <hi>14.</hi> Vaſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. cit. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> for it is wiſely ſaid, that he is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly man who ſhall ſay to the King. Thou doſt wickedly. As this is the judgement of the Fathers and Moderne Divines, ſo is it the common judgement of all the Schoolemen, as they ſay themſelves.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſince in Monarchicall government, the ſupreme Prince hath ſuch abſolute power, it were well done to change it into <hi>a mixt</hi> government. If we had ſuffered the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to remaine an <hi>abſolute Monarch,</hi> (as you do your King)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112413:4"/>we had never gotten ſo much of our wils, and his Holineſſe the Pope would have been hindered from the fruition of his law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>ſupremacie</hi> over Emperors: and if you ſhall endure this your government, it will bee a great impediment to the <hi>ends</hi> you aime at. For this cauſe, <hi>regimen temperatum ex Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia, Ariſtocratia, &amp; Democratia mitius eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> its a more milde government that is mixt of Monarchie, Ariſtocracie, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracie. You doe well then to aime at it, for it is our advice. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in that ſame place ſpeaketh home to you.<note place="margin">It llar. de Rom. Pont. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Praſides provinciarum vel civitatum ne ſint regis vicarii, aut annui ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, ſed veri principes; qui &amp; imperio ſummi principis obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant, &amp; interim provinciam vel civitatem ſuam non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam alie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am, ſed ut propriam moderentur.</hi> Let not the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Provinces, or cities be the Kings deputies, or yeerely Judges, but let them be true Princes; who may both be obedient to the command of their chiefe Prince, and in the meane time govern their province or citie, not as it were another mans, but as their own; by this meanes, both a kinde of Monarchie, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocracie, and Democracie may have place in the republicke.</p>
            <p>Proceed therefore to the perfecting the good work which you have begun. Conſider the power you have had, as abſolute Lords over your Tenants, and as <hi>Princes and Chiefe</hi> over your <hi>Clans,</hi> every one of you being <hi>little Kings,</hi> like <hi>Dionyſius Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi,</hi> commanding and ruling your Vaſſals, as you pleaſed; but ſee now how it is abridged by a new form of juſtice, by introducing <hi>Juſtice of peace,</hi> &amp;c. Which (to ſay the truth) though it tend to the ſettlement and peace of the Kingdome, yet it mainly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth your former domineering, &amp; makes your Vaſſals look more to <hi>the King and his Lawes, then to you and your commands.</hi> It is certain by our well grounded principles, that there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that your King of Scotland ſhould be a more abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch then the Emperor of Rome; he is not like your King an <hi>abſolute Prince by ſucceſſion;</hi> but a <hi>conditionall</hi> prince by <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> tyed by ſuch ſtrict conditions, which if he tranſgreſſe, he may be thruſt from them. For firſt, the Prince Electors may chuſe whom they pleaſe to be Emperour, by their Emperiall Lawes. Secondly, the Princes Electors have power to judge and cognoſce upon the Emperors fault<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Thirdly, if they finde him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112413:5"/>worthy of depoſition, they may depoſe him. And by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Elect his own conſent, it is ſtatute and ordained, that if the Princes Electors, or the whole body of the Kingdome ſhall withſtand, or take arms againſt the Emperour, it ſhalbe accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lawfull without any crime of <hi>rebellion. Ex ſanctione Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici</hi> 7. <hi>&amp; aurea bulla Caroli</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; capitulatione Caeſarta.</hi> Read this capitulation in <hi>Melchior Goladaſt. tom.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 424. which is thus, <hi>Quòd ſi nos ipſi, (inquit Imperator) quod abſit, aut quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſucceſſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtrorum, quod non ſperamus proceſſu tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris aliquo, huic noſtrae ſtatutioni, aut ordinationi contravenire voluerit aut eam retractare aut alio quevis mode violare pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumſerit: praeſentium literaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> autoritate, quas mera noſtra au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritate, &amp; poteſtatis regiae plenitudine, ex certa noſtra Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>statis ſcientia, nec non cum conſenſu &amp; bene placito praefato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſacri Romani imperii principum Electorum, in robur per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuae firmitatis ſancivimus, ex tunc tam ipſi Electores quam caeteri Principes, eccleſiastici &amp; ſaculares, praelati, comites, barones, nobiles &amp; communitates ſacrinostri imperii, univerſi ac ſinguli praeſentes &amp; ſuturi, licitum habeant ſine rebellionis aut infidelitatis crimine, reſistendi ac contradicendi nobis, &amp; ſucceſſoribus noſtris, Romanorum regibus, vel imperat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ribus, in perpetuam libertatem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I wil aſſure you, his Holineſſe the Pope was not ſleeping when the Emperour was thus clogged: and albeit it may bee thought that this change of ſimple Monarchy in this mixt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, hath beene a chiefe ground of all the bloudy war of Germany this long time by gone, which would not have bin if it had remained an abſolute Monarchy: for while it ſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an abſolute Monarchie in the Primitive Church, their plea was, <hi>Rogamus Caeſar, non pugnamus:</hi> and, <hi>aliter nec debeo, nec poſſum reſiſtere.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>l. contra Auxen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Yet let not this trouble Us: for herein is fulfil'd the prophecy of Chriſt while he ſaid, <hi>He came not to ſend peace, but the ſword.</hi> And againe, this change is neceſſary, for elſe his Holineſs the Pope ſhould be ſubject to the Emperor, according to that of <hi>Paul, Let every ſoul be ſubject to ſuperior powers:</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he neither is nor ought to be.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> And therefore <hi>Bernard</hi> is herein deceived himſelfe, while he makes this a generall rule without exception,<note place="margin">Bernard Epiſt. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> ſaying, <hi>Qui conatur ab ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regula excipere, conatur
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112413:5"/>decipere:</hi> for both <hi>Pope</hi> with us, and <hi>people</hi> with you muſt be a excepted. The Church of God hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ter'd too much already in the Primitive times, ſhe hath been too long in the <hi>Category of Paſsion,</hi> crying with teares <hi>Oramus non pugnamus:</hi> ſhe ought now to be in the <hi>predicament of action,</hi> with <hi>Pugnamus &amp; ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> holding (that I may uſe your own words) <hi>a ſupplication in the one hand, and a ſword in the other</hi> To this purpoſe Maſter <hi>Andrew Ramſey</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Edenburgh</hi> ſaid pretty well, that it was Gods will that the Primitive Church ſhould confirme the truth by <hi>ſuffering,</hi> and that now the truth being confirmed, its his will that we defend the truth by <hi>action,</hi> in reſiſting Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants; and what war is better then that which is for Religion? But here an <hi>Auticoveuanter</hi> wil reply perchance, &amp; ſay. Where did ever any ſuffer under Tyrants for defending of your Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall government of active or ruling-elders, and of paſſive or ruled-elders, which had its firſt beginning from <hi>Calvin</hi> in ſome ſort; but as you have it, it was never in the world till the yeer 1638. For in <hi>Geneva</hi> it is only proper to the <hi>ſupreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate</hi> to chuſe the <hi>Lay-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lders:</hi> for they are only Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the <hi>Seigniori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> neither hath the <hi>Miniſter</hi> any voyce in their Election, much leſſe the <hi>Multitude:</hi> and all that <hi>Calvin</hi> gave them, is <hi>praeſſe moribus,</hi> and in Church matters they are called <hi>ad conſiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> but not <hi>ad conſenſum.</hi> But now in Scotland, not only the whole Church takes the <hi>ſupreme power</hi> to it ſelfe, but alſo every pariſh takes upon it to be an <hi>abſolute indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſociety,</hi> quire contrary to the practice of <hi>Geneva,</hi> chuſing their Miniſters and Elders alſo without number, and to thoſe Elders <hi>equal power</hi> is given with the Miniſter, in Presbyteries and Aſſemblies, in giving <hi>deciſive</hi> ſentence in matters of faith, and deciding of controverſies, whereof, God knowes, they are moſt ignorant: and in a word, they want nothing of the power of the Miniſter, but that they preach not, nor baptiſe in publike congregations: &amp; yet its common to ſee <hi>Lay-men</hi> among them in private Conventicles to take upon them the calling of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in preaching and praying. Or where did any at any time ſuffer for abjuring Epiſcopacie as an antichriſtian government? ſo this being a truth never yet confirmed by <hi>ſuffering,</hi> muſt not now be defended by <hi>reſiſting,</hi> according to <hi>Ramſeyes</hi> own rule,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112413:6"/>but being an Article of his negative faith, it muſt firſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by ſuffering. I would enquire then (ſayes the Anticove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanter) of <hi>Ramſey,</hi> if he dare ſuffer for it, and be the <hi>Protomar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> in this cauſe? but he would be like the man that came to the marriage without the wedding garment, <hi>dumb and ſpeechleſſe.</hi> Or if he ſpeak, it would bee negative like his faith, ſaying with <hi>Athanaſius, Quod non à patribus profectum eſt-ſed nuper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum, quid de co aliud exiſt imari debeat quam illud ipſum cujus Paulus mentionem facit,</hi> 1. Timoth. 4.1.</p>
            <p>But finding my ſelf dig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſing, I will return to the point, which I was about, concerning government. Seeing this mixt govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is moſt conducible for your ends, it were requiſite that your Nobles would aſſume to themſelves <hi>Princely Authoriti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (as is thought ſome of you have done) &amp; make progreſſe in this good work. For (let me ſpeake it between me and you) till you Kings government be changed, you ſhall never lawfully reſiſt him. For I have peruſed all your Divines and find them all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the lawfulneſſe of reſiſting ſuch a King as yours is: but at the moſt they hold it lawfull <hi>in ſome caſes</hi> only to reſiſt <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventionall</hi> or <hi>conditionall Princes.</hi> Hence it was that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Wittenberge</hi> were moſt oppoſite to our doctrine of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſisting Princes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>h.</note> in their publike ſermons, but when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held upon what expreſſe <hi>conditions</hi> the Emperour was <hi>elected</hi> to the Empire to the which he was not <hi>borne,</hi> then they ſaid, <hi>Docuimus quidem hactenus nullo modo reſiſtendum eſſe Magistratui ignoravimus vero ex legum civilium praeſcripto, id in certis quibuſdam caſibus, etiam legitimè fieripoſſe.</hi> We have hitherto taught that the Magiſtrate by no manner of way ought to be reſiſted: for we did not know that by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of the civill law, it might in ſome certain caſes be lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done. So <hi>Pareus</hi> (as you know) was the laſt that wrote upon that ſubject, whoſe opinion when it was condemned by your learned Divines; his ſon <hi>Philippu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pareus</hi> purpoſing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his fathers opinion, yeelds his ſword<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and giveth over the combate even at the entrie,<note place="margin">Append. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>13.</hi> ad Rom.</note> in thoſe words: <hi>Loquitur enim D. parens meus, ut &amp; Theologicaeteri juxta cum politicis &amp; juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſultis iis quorum ſententiam ac judicium in hoc argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſequutus eſt parens noſter, non derege abſoluta poteſtate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112413:6"/>indut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſed de principibus ſub conditione admiſsis.</hi> That is, my father, and the reſt of the Theolognes, Polititians and Juriſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalts, whoſe ſentence &amp; judgement in this argument my father hath followed, do not ſpeake of a King endued with <hi>abſolute power,</hi> but of Princes who are <hi>conditionally</hi> admitted. And therefore if you would make any lawfull reſiſtance for time to come, its moſt neceſſarie that you labour for a change of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment now, and make your ſelves free. We have Scripture for us, <hi>But if thou mayeſt be made free, uſe it rather.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.26</note> 
               <hi>Claudian</hi> did but deceive himſelf, neither can I endure him while he ſaies</p>
            <q>
               <l>Fallitur ogregio quiſquis ſub principe credit</l>
               <l>Servitium: nunquam Libertus gratior extat</l>
               <l>Quam ſub rege pio.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Nay, I ſay, <hi>Quam ſub rege meo,</hi> ſuch a King as is <hi>mine;</hi> ſo <hi>mine,</hi> that I may un-make him againe, whom I have made <hi>mine.</hi> Try this at your Parliament, ſee if your King will yeeld to this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which I have told you of the Roman Emperour, to <hi>ſubject</hi> himſelf to you his Subjects, that the <hi>Majeſty</hi> may reſide in you. <hi>Audentes fortuna juvat.</hi> Your ſucceſſe may be gloryed of. Your King hath yeelded ſo much unto you, that you may bee confident to have this yeelded alſo. If he had been a mercileſſe Tyrant, he had been ſo farre from granting you all your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that he might have impoſed moe burthens upon you, who did refuſe obedience to that which is judged by all your prime Doctors to be lawfull. Thus thoſe two famous Doctors of yours <hi>Gualter</hi> &amp; <hi>Bullinger</hi> did write in an Epiſtle ſent to the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks in England, who had oppoſed themſelves, as you do, to the Service-book of England. <hi>If in caſe</hi> (ſay they) <hi>any of the people be perſwaded that thoſe things ſavour of Poperie, let them be taught the contrary, and perfectly inſtructed therein: and if ſo be, through the importunate crying out hereupon before the people by ſome men, many be diſquieted; let them beware that do ſo, that they bring no greater yoke upon their own necks, and provoke Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>her Majeſty, and bring many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters in ſuch danger, as they cannot rid themſelves again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will ſhew you an example hereof, which fell out in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie at <hi>Magdeburge,</hi> and within the Territories of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe Albertus.</hi> The Prince required the Miniſters to follow
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112413:7"/>the whole book of Auguſtan's confeſſion, where is a Liturgie that hath all that is in yours, which you have condemned; but ſome m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ceremonies, and doth retain the name of the Maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book. Refuſall thereof was made by the Nobility, Gentry, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Citizens, even as ſome of all this ranke among you have done. The Court hereon ran upon another deliberation, propoſing Articles, which doe not alter the doctrine and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, but thruſt upon them m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Ceremonies (<hi>which yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may well enough be borne,</hi> ſayes <hi>Melancton,</hi> whom you call the light of Germanie) adding withall a threatning, that they, who will not follow this preſcription, ſhould depart the Land. Upon this ſome too forward Miniſters affirmed, <hi>It were good to affright the Court with ſome terrible writing, with the ſcare of Sedition, and with this Scar-crow to repreſſe and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der further alteration. Ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ricus Flaccius</hi> was chiefe man, the <hi>Demetrius</hi> in this upreare, crying out (as your Miniſters did) <hi>That rather deſolation ſhould be made of the Church:</hi> and, <hi>Princes are to be frighted with terror of Inſurrection.</hi> But for my part (ſaid <hi>Melancton I will be author of no ſuch ſoure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi> Whereupon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt of the Miniſters did ſlander <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton</hi> (as <hi>Anticovenante<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> ſay you doe them) as Popiſhly affec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed,<note place="margin">Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h Melan. part. <hi>2</hi> pag. <hi>90.91.100.</hi>
               </note> and was upon the plot to reduce Poperie, and wrote to <hi>Calvin</hi> to this effect. But truly I am of <hi>Beza's</hi> opinion, that they accuſed him <hi>without cauſe,</hi> as afterward <hi>Calvin</hi> knew more truely. For (ſayes <hi>Beza</hi>) <hi>at the beginning it was not knowne with what intention that evill ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>0.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and whole Troup of the Flaccinians raiſed ſo many tumults, and now at this time doth hinder the work of God againſt Papiſts.</hi> Thus <hi>Beza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is true indeed, that the <hi>Flaccinians,</hi> who thus did combine againſt their Prince, did more advance our cauſe, then <hi>Melanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on.</hi> and the remanent of your Doctors; whoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, that the Church ſhould not be troubled by refuſing the Service book: and (as <hi>Melanctons</hi> words are) <hi>to wrangle about a Surpleſſe, or the like matter; where wiſe-men will exclaime againſt us, that we withstand and diſobey Authority, and nouriſh contention with a fooliſh forwardneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing it hath pleaſed your King to deale thus with you, to lay <hi>no heavier burdens</hi> upon you, who have complained
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112413:7"/>of a <hi>light one:</hi> but to grant you all that hitherto you have p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned; ſee if you can obtaine of him a change of the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But I pray you, doe it with great prudence and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, laying ſuch grounds, as you may firmely build upon them. For, if at the firſt you declare your ſelfe, and ſay plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Sir, wee deſire your government changed, he will reſile, and not grant it: and to proceed ſuddenly from one extremitie to another, is difficult. Therefore firſt of all, by ſuch faire wayes as you can, bee inſtant to take from him his <hi>negative voyce</hi> in Synods and Parliaments, which is a thing ſo eſſentiall to Soveraigntie, that it ſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alleth with it. For he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtitute of this P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llar, if in Parliaments by pluraliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of voyces it be carried, that you will not <hi>have this man to raign over you,</hi> of neceſſitie he mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be gone. Secondly, ſee if you can take from him the <hi>power of making Laws,</hi> and let the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Synods bee the <hi>Law makers.</hi> You have taken this <hi>de facto</hi> already in your large pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation, in <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1638. where you ſay in expreſſe terms, <hi>that the Parliament and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned are the Law-makers, and the Law-interpreters.</hi> As you have it <hi>de facto,</hi> ſee if you can get it <hi>de jure,</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law; which if you obtaine, you may thinke you have attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your end: for, if not the King but Parliament and Synods be the <hi>Legiſlators,</hi> hee muſt he ſubject to ſuch Laws as it ſhall pleaſe them to make, who are the two <hi>Supreme judicatories,</hi> to which in your proteſtation you appeale, from the King and his Councell: thus ſubjecting your King to Parliament and Synod, which is a thing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee can hardly ſuffer. But to pleaſe him withall, appoint him to be the <hi>Executioner</hi> of the Laws, and ſo let him have the name of a King. But it may be, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat if he have no more but the execution, of your Lawes, that he ſhall rid himſelfe of that too, if you grant him no more power; becauſe men will ſay, He <hi>is not your King, but your Officer, or H! &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly, if ſo bee, that he ſhall be content with what portion of authoritie <hi>you judge</hi> ſufficient, take heed that hee fall not upon you who have thus curbed him, and execute the laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you: and therefore to make all cocke ſure, becauſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe all by himſelfe, but muſt have Officers under him; let this bee granted to you alſo, to be <hi>Chuſers of his Officers,</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112413:8"/>let thoſe be ſuch as you know moſt expedient for you: and ſo they ſhall be rather <hi>your men,</hi> then <hi>His.</hi> I heard that all this was motioned by you, but you have not ſhowne me what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe it hath taken.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> I have dwelt long upon this neceſſary point of the change of Government, and therefore I proceede to a ſecond head, where into wee fully conſpire, and it is a very fit preparative to this intended change.<note place="margin">Coven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. 3.</note> And I cannot but applaud you for rejecting that former errour, to defend that Kings are of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution,</hi> and doe now hold with us, that they are of <hi>humane Inſtitution by poſitive Lawes. Inregnis hominum potestas regis eſt à popule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bell de Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, 2. cap. 19.</note> 
               <hi>quia populus facit regem.</hi> In the Kingdome of men, the power of the King is from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſayes <hi>Bellarmine:</hi> and commends Navarre, <hi>Qui non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitat affirmare, nunquam populum ita potestatem ſuam in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem transferre, quin illam ſibi in habitu retineat, ut in certis quibuſdam caſibus etiam</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, aſtu.</note> 
               <hi>actu recipere poteſt.</hi> Who doth not doubt to ſay, that the people did never ſo transferre their power to the King, but they did retaine it <hi>habitually</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; ſo that in certaine caſes they may <hi>actually</hi> take it from him againe. Let all Proteſtant Doctors condemne this, yet let it never repent you to have received light from us. The beſt works that ever <hi>Augustixe</hi> wrote, were the books of <hi>retrectations;</hi> and the beſt workes that you can doe, is to forſake your errors. You ſay the <hi>people makes the Magiſtrate, and may be without him, and have been many a yeare without him.</hi> The <hi>Majesty</hi> doth remaine in the <hi>people,</hi> and therefore, as it is ſaid in the Goſpel, <hi>May I not doe with my owne what I pleaſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bell, de cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie lib. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.</note> So ſay wee, <hi>Poteſtas immediate eſt tanquam in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in tota multitudine, &amp; ſi cauſa legitimè adſit, poteſt multitudo mutare regnum in Ariſtocratiam &amp; Democrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</hi> The power is <hi>immediately,</hi> as in the <hi>ſubject,</hi> in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and if there be a lawfull cauſe, the multitude may change the Kingdome into an Ariſtocracie, or Democracie. When the King becommeth an enemy to the Common wealth, hee ought to be removed, <hi>Melius eſt ut pereat unus, quam unitas.</hi> And therefore you may not without reaſon ſay (as in your Sions Plea) to his Majeſty, <hi>Wee muſt not loſe you, and the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112413:8"/>Kingdome, by proferring your fancies, and groundleſſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, before ſound reaſon. You ſhould complain to the heart that the head is much diſtempered; The Lyon muſt be cured of the Kings evill.</hi> The Potter may deſtroy the veſſell which hee hath made himſelfe. (But I pray you let this be ſpoken under the Roſe; for if we too much divulge it, it will make both you and us moſt odious to all princes, who will keepe us at ſuch a low ebbe that we ſhall never be able to riſe againſt them when wee thinke it neceſſary.) When the ſhepheard becommeth a Wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, let the dogs cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e him away: he is for the people, and the people is not for him; when he turnes to their hurt, let one who is for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r good be put in his place: for you know who ſaid, <hi>Virtuti, non gener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> debetur regnum.</hi> And it is better to have Kings by <hi>election</hi> then <hi>ſucceſſion.</hi> And therefore you doe moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> learnedly reaſon from the <hi>unreaſonableneſs and abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of thoſe Court Paraſites</hi> (in your learned informations for Defenſive armes againſt the King) <hi>who attribute ſuch illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited power to their Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenanters in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> at for D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nſive. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g. 1.</note> 
               <hi>that they looſe all the bonds of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill ſociety againſt all the bonds of oathes and lawes; ſuffering the Prince to doe what he pleaſeth, to the ruine of Religion, the Church and Kingdome; and the people ſhall do nothing but ſuffer themſelves to be maſſacred or elſe ſtie, which is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> In parallel to this we ſay thus: <hi>The danger is ſo evident,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 5.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evitable, that God hath not ſufficiently provided for our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and the preſervation of the Church and holy Lawes, if there were no way to reſtraine ſuch wicked Princes, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this were (as you ſay) <hi>to expone all to the fury of the Prince.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> And therfore we conclude in the ſame place with thoſe words, <hi>The bond and obligation wee haue entered into for the ſervice of Chriſt and his Church, far exceeds all other duties which wee owe to any humane creature: &amp; therefore where the obedience to the inferiour hindereth the ſervice of the other, which is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, we muſt by law and order diſcharge our ſelves of the inferiour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenanters inform for Defenſive.</note> This our concluſion is moſt conſonant to the words and ſenſe of your ſecond and fourth argument for war.</p>
            <p>And ſince you were put to this neceſſity to take up armes for your defence, notwithſtanding of your Kings <hi>specious pretences,</hi> who could condemne you to preſſe and urge the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112413:9"/>people, by your reaſons to take up armes, to reſiſt the violence of your King,<note place="margin">Covenanters inform for Defenſive. 57. <hi>Sigebert in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1088.</note> who was <hi>furiouſly inveding you</hi> as you ſay? and to thruſt all away from their places that did withſtand you, as traitors to you, the Church and Countrey, and unworthy of your <hi>ſociety.</hi> I do not regard, neither need you to be offended at that idle ſpeech of <hi>Sigebert;</hi> neither would I heare him, if he did not aske leave of all good men (from which number I will not be excluded) to ſpeake, while he ſayes thus, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſpeak, with the leave of all good men, this onely novelty. I will not ſay here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie was not crept into the world (before the dayes of</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ellde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand) <hi>that Prieſts ſhould teach the people that they owe no ſubjection to evill Kings, and that although they have ſworne fidelitie to him yet they muſt yeeld him none; neither may they be counted perjured for holding againſt their King, but rather he that obeyeth the King is excommunicate, and he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belleth against the King, is abſolved from the blemiſh of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſloyaltie and perjurie. &amp;c.</hi> Thus he. And is this a matter to be condemned, I pray you? Doe we not cleerely ſee this perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among your ſelves? the King himſelfe will approve of it: for you are confident of it, while you ſay: <hi>Wee are very confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of his Majeſties approbation to the integritie of our hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>1633.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and peaceableneſſe of our wayes and actions all this time paſt; and doe proteſt that we will ſtill adhere to our former proceedings mutuall defence, &amp;c.</hi> And good reaſon, for rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion for ſuch an important buſineſſe againſt a King, cannot bee diſloyaltie; and they that have not followed your courſe, juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerve <hi>Excommunication</hi> and <hi>Baniſhment. Athanaſius</hi> was but too ſilly a man, being under the tyrannie of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> the <hi>Arrian Hereticke,</hi> that did not incite the people to <hi>rebellion,</hi> or to promove the deſignes of the Emperours bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was Orthodoxe, and worthier of the Crown. Which if he had done, he might have made a better Apologie to the Emperour <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> who charged him with the ſame, as if he had ſtirred up his brother, and the people againſt him. If he had done ſo, he might have made <hi>Peters</hi> Apologie, <hi>Its bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to obey God then man.</hi> But becauſe he did it not, hee makes an Apologie moſt beſeeming a coward, who did not (as you did) <hi>with counſell and courage lead the people to war againſt their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112413:9"/>Prince:</hi> but ſayes thus, <hi>Vincat quaſo, apud te,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> 
               <hi>veritas: &amp; ne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquas ſuſpicionem contra univerſam eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quaſitalia ant cogitentur aut ſcribantur à Chriſtianis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> potiſsimum Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopis.</hi> Let truth I pray thee prevaile with thee, and leave not a ſuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cion againſt the Catholick Church, as if ſuch things were either thought or written by Chriſtians, and eſpecially by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. <hi>I am not ſo mad, I am not beſide my ſelfe, O Emperour, that thou ſhouldſt ſuſpect I had any ſuch thought; I am not ſo mad, neither have I forgotten the voyce of God, which ſaith, Curſe not the King in thy heart, nor backbite the mightie in the ſecrets of thy chamber: for the birds of the ayre ſhall tell it, and the fowles that ſhe ſhall betray it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Covenanter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inform. for D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fenſive. § 4.</note>This man was too fearefull: but you were of another ſpirit, encouraging the people, and dehorting them from <hi>being afraid of ſhadowes;</hi> yea, your Prieſts were good patterns to the reſt to follow. There was one of them, who is worthy (if you could permit Images) to have his Statue ingraven in Marble,<note place="margin">Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to eternize him to the worlds end, who went ſo ſtoutly to the Camp upon his horſe, with two Carabins at his Sadle, two Piſtols at his ſide, with a broad Scottiſh ſword; thoſe five weapons were like unto <hi>Davids</hi> ſive ſmooth ſtones which he tooke out of the brooke to kill <hi>Goliah</hi> with. This <hi>David</hi> no doubt would have killed ſive Engliſh at the firſt encounter with his five deadly weapons, and would have returned with triumph, ſaying with <hi>Paul, I have fought a good fight:</hi> for,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7. Nehem. 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould ſuch a man as</hi> he <hi>flie?</hi> But if any ſhall produce the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of divers generall Councels, ordaining Clergie men that beare arms to be degraded and put from their place: And that of <hi>Davenant, Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> gladium</hi> verbi <hi>promittit, non</hi> ferri:<note place="margin">Davenant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. quaeſt. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam <hi>ſuadet, non</hi> pugnam. Chriſt promiſeth to his Paſtors the ſword of the word, and not the ſword of Iron: he perſwades to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lie, but not to ſight: the anſwer is eaſie. Thoſe generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels though not <hi>intoto,</hi> yet <hi>pro tanto,</hi> are like your 6. generall or n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tionall Councels, which you have condemned, becauſe they were againſt you: and <hi>Davonant</hi> is a Biſhop, and ſo your adverſary.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> A third errour wherewith wee were formerly toſſed by you, is now removed, it concerneth the Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112413:10"/>which you at laſt, being put to it, doe acknowledge to belong to the Church, not to the King. What hath hee to doe there?</p>
            <q>
               <l>Let Kings take care of civill ſtate,</l>
               <l>Let Church, of Church-matters debate.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This was the preſumption and errour of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. King of England,<note place="margin">Bell. de Rom. Pontiſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> obſerveth. <hi>Is enim ſe caput eccleſiae Anglicanae conſtituit, &amp; eodem modo cenſuit alios principes capita ſuprema in ſuis ditionibus eſſe.</hi> For he made himſelfe Head of the Church, and after the ſame manner judged other Princes to bee ſupreme heads within their owne Dominions. And thus King <hi>Charles</hi> would alſo be: therefore in your <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations,</hi> you declare that it is your ancient grievance,<note place="margin">Proteſtat. 18. Decemb. 1638.</note> 
               <hi>That his Majeſtie takes upon him, that ſpirituall power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, which properly belongeth to Christ, as onely King and Head of his Kirk The miniſtery and execution whereof is onely given to ſuch as beare Eccleſiaſticall government of the ſame So that in his Majeſties perſon ſome men preſſe to erect a Popedome.</hi> And all your Proteſtant Divines do hold the ſame doctrine, as ſo many <hi>Court Paraſites.</hi> The Fathers went too far on this way,<note place="margin">Auguſt. contra l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ae lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. p. <hi>92.</hi>
               </note> I will but name <hi>Auguſtine: All men</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>ought to ſerve God, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, as men: in another ſort by ſeveral gifts &amp; offices, by the which, ſome do this, ſome do that. No private perſon could command idols to be baniſhed cleane from amongſt men which was ſo long before propheſied.<note place="margin">Idem contra Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>51.</hi>
                  </note> Therfore Kings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beſide their duty to ſerve God common with all men) have, in that they be Kings, how to ſerve the Lord in ſuch ſort, as none can do, which are not Kings; for in this, Kings, as they are Kings, ſerve the Lord</hi> (<hi>as God by</hi> David <hi>enjoyned them,</hi> Pſal. 1.) <hi>if in their Kingdomes they command that which is good, and prohibite that which is evill not in civill affaires only, but alſo in matters concerning Divine Religion, &amp;c.</hi> This man is ſo confident that in his 50. <hi>Epiſtle</hi> he cryeth out, <hi>Who being in their right wits dare alledge the contrary?</hi> But truly the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> held the better part, they durſt alledge the contrary; ſo dare <hi>We,</hi> ſo dare <hi>you doe: macti viri virtute novâ.</hi> The fathers judgement in ſuch ſtate matters is not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by his Holineſſe the Pope. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> our truſtie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112413:10"/>Champion ſpeaketh better for you: That the civill Magiſtrate <hi>regit homines, ut homines ſunt, &amp; magis ratione corporum quam animarum:</hi> but on the contrary, the Church Governour <hi>regit homines, ut Chriſtiani ſunt, &amp; magis ratione animarum quam corporum: ille habet pro fine temporalem quietem, &amp; ſalutem populi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> iſte vitam &amp; ſempiternam foelicitatem: ille utitur naturalibus legibus. &amp; inſtitutis humanis; iſte legibus divinis.</hi> The King governeth men as they are men, and rather in regard of their bodies then their ſoules: but the Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour governeth men as they are Chriſtians, and rather in regard of their ſoules then their bodies. The end of the one is to procure the temporall quiet and ſafetie of the people; the other hath for his end, everlaſting life and happineſſe: the one uſeth naturall Lawes and humane inſtitutions; but the other uſeth Divine Lawes.</p>
            <p>And whereas your Doctors ſay, that the King is the Keeper of the Tables and the Miniſter of God for our good, and if for our good, then chiefly for our <hi>principall good,</hi> the good of our ſoules; to have a care of Religion according to the examples of the religious Kings under the Law, and Chriſtian Princes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, &amp;c. Thoſe, and many ſuch like idle arguments are not worthy that I ſhould ſtand to anſwer them, eſpecially in an Epiſtle; for there is no ſuch need of Kings, <hi>the people may well enough bee without them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenanters informat. for Defenſive. arg. 3.</note> 
               <hi>for there was none till Cains dayes,</hi> as you ſay: The Church was well governed in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive time while there was no Chriſtian King. <hi>Ad annos fermeè</hi> 30<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>nullus fuit in Eccleſia Chriſtianus Princeps ſecularis.</hi> For the ſpace of 300 yeers there was no ſecular Chriſtian Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce in the Church, ſayes <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> And therefore, ſayes he,<note place="margin">Bell. de laicis, cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Christus Eccleſiam regendam Petro &amp; Epiſcopis commiſit, non Tyberio &amp; ejus Praefectis:</hi> Hee committed the government of his Church, to <hi>Peter</hi> and the Biſhops, not to <hi>Tyberius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and his Officers. He ſaid to <hi>Peter, Feed my ſheep;</hi> not ſo to Kings, but, <hi>Doe my Prophets no wrong.</hi> The Church-men muſt give an account to God of mens ſouls, Kings have no ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to make, as our <hi>Stapleton</hi> ſayes well with you &amp; therfore concludes, that not Kings, but the Church is to be obeyed in Eccleſiaſticall buſineſſes; according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112413:11"/>praepoſitit veſtris. Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves unto them for they watch for your ſoule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13 17.</note> You doe then as it becommeth you, not to regard the Kings words, nor ohey his Proclamations: but to perſwade the people (that I may uſe your own words) <hi>to ſubmit themſelves obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to follow their Leaders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenanters inform for Peſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive.</note> 
               <hi>whom God at this time hath largely furniſhed with counſell and courage for the good of his Church and Kingdome:</hi> The reaſon why they ſhould follow them, and not be carried away with the Kings Proclamations: quia poteſtas civilis ſubjecta eſt poteſtati ſpirituals quando utra<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pars eſt ejuſdem reipub.<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtianae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A fourth error which you with good ſucceſſe have aboliſhed, that you deny the power of convocating and diſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies to belong to the <hi>Supreme Magiſtrate.</hi> In the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation in <hi>July</hi> 1638. you maintaine your <hi>power of convocating Aſſemblies:</hi> therefore in the 27. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1638. it was well put in among your Inſtructions before the Aſſemblies,<note place="margin">VIII. Inſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>that the ableſt man in each Pariſh ſhould be provided to diſpute Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate ſupremt Magiſtratús in Ecccleſiaſticis, praeſertim in convocandis Conciliis.</hi> Its your wiſdome to aſſemble when hee commands you, ſo long as it is conducible for your ends; but yet you have power to aſſemble in a <hi>Nationall Aſſemblie,</hi> in what place of the Kingdome you pleaſe.<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Socrates</hi> did ſmell too much of a <hi>Court Paraſite,</hi> while he ſaid, we make mention of Emperors throughout this Hiſtory, for that ſince they became Chriſtians, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccleſiaſtical matters depend on them &amp; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Synods have been, and yet are called by their appointment. He offended you who ſaid that as <hi>Moſes</hi> is <hi>cuſtos utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulae,</hi> ſo is he <hi>cuſtos utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tubae:</hi> as the civill Magiſtrate is keeper of both the <hi>Tables;</hi> ſo hee is keeper of both the <hi>ſilver Trumpets,</hi> for <hi>war,</hi> for calling of <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> and diſmiſſing of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that you would but blow the Trumpet of <hi>Sedition,</hi> it (without the Kings authority) you ſhould convocate Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles either for <hi>peace,</hi> or for <hi>warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Hamilton</hi> was too preſumptuous, being called with the Kings Authoritie, to diſcharge your laſt Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, which (as you ſaid well) was to <hi>raiſe Chriſt's Court:</hi> and therefore, it was not ill adviſed by one of you, <hi>that ſeeing the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112413:11"/>Marqueſſe was faithfull to his Maſter the King, ſo you ought to be faithfull to your Maſter the King of kings Jeſus Chriſt, and to defend his Royall prerogative above all the Kings of the earth.</hi> In your anſwer to the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Hamilious</hi> Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you affirme that <hi>your Eccleſiasticall juriſdiction is inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent,</hi> and in your <hi>Zions Plea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> you ſay, that your Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian diſcipline <hi>is the Scepter of Chriſt, ſwaying his own houſe according to his hearts deſire, the ſoul the chief Commander in the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mp Royall;</hi> and your <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ravers</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">De diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p E <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. <hi>142.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Huic diſciplinae omnes orbis Principes &amp; Monarchas faſces ſuos ſubmittere, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere neceſſe eſt:</hi> There is a neceſſity that all the Princes and Monarchs ſhould ſubmit their Scepters, and obey this diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. And your <hi>Mae Lellan</hi> (whom ſome call a foole) ſpake not fooliſhly, while he preached, <hi>that the King had no more to do to meddle with your Aſſemblies; then you have to meddle with his Parliaments.</hi> It was wiſely then dont by you, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting any <hi>proteſtation</hi> or <hi>appellation</hi> from your Aſſemblie by the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and their adherents, to the Kings Majeſtie; for ſuch appellations ought not to be, ſeeing there is none <hi>Supreme</hi> above your Nationall Aſſemblies. And therefore, as you have not hitherto regarded their proteſtation and appellation, but have proceeded againſt them to <hi>depoſition,</hi> and <hi>excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo continue, and be not diſmaid though they ſhould renue their proteſtations and appellations, even in the words of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> in proteſting againſt, and appealing from the partiall coun ell of <hi>Tyrus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Athanaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> polo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> which appellation and proteſtation of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> and the reſt of the orthodox Biſhops was in theſe words: <hi>Becauſe we ſee many things ſpitefully contrived againſt us, and much wrong offered the Catholik Church under our rames we be forced to requeſt that the debating of our matters may bee kept for the Princes moſt excellent perſon. We cannot beare the drifts and injuries of our enemies; and therefore, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the cauſe to be referred to the most religious and devout Emperour, before whom we ſhall be ſuffered to ſtand in our own defence, and plead the right of the Church, &amp;c.</hi> If thoſe your Biſhops flying to the King, as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and the reſt of the orthodox Biſhops did to the Emperour, ſhall procure an edict or command from the King, (as thoſe did from the Emperor) to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112413:12"/>charge you all to appeare before him to plead your cauſe, you ought not to appeare as that miſerable Synod of <hi>Tyrus</hi> did: The Edict was ſo peremptory, that they durſt not reſiſt. The Edict was in theſe words: <hi>Your Synod hath decreed I know not what in a tumult and uproare, while you ſeeke to pervert truth by your peſtilent diſorder for hatred againſt your fellow Biſhops. But the divine providence will (I doubt not) ſcatter the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe of your contention, and make it plaine in our ſight, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Aſſembly had any regard of truth, or not. You muſt therefore all of you reſort hither, to ſhew the reaſon of your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, for ſo doth it ſeeme good and expedient to me; to which end, I willed this reſcript to be ſent you, that as many of you as were preſent at the Councell of</hi> Tyrus, <hi>without delay repaire to the place of our abode, there to give an account how ſincerely &amp; ſoundly you have judged, &amp; that before me, whom your ſelves ſhal not deny to be the ſincere Miniſter of God in</hi> ſuch caſes &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I ſay then, if you ſhall receive ſuch a charge from your King, you ſhould not obey: (for in your ſenſe that is, <hi>To betray the Royall prerogative of your King Jeſus Chriſt</hi>) but returne the anſwer of <hi>Core, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> with ingemination, <hi>We will not come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m 16.12, 14. J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 2 31.</note> 
               <hi>we will not come:</hi> or your Lords, Lay-Elders may return that of <hi>Jeremy, We are Lords, We will no more come unto thee.</hi> And if your King will not be content with your anſwer, proſecute your begun courſe with all diligence and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe; having begun in the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> end not in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> but go on with that which they call diſorders, till <hi>you get the King in your power, and then he ſhal know what ſubjects you will be.</hi> If the people of one citie falling in <hi>ſedition</hi> for matters of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> ſo prevailed &amp; paſſed all power of reſiſting,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> that <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the Emperour was fain to come to an open place without his <hi>Crown.</hi> &amp; by Heraulds to ſignifie to the people, that he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die with a very good will to reſigne the Empire into their hands: how much more may you who have many cities, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing your courſes force your King to reſigne his Crown of Scotland? And howbeit the people of that citie ſeeing the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror in ſo pitiful a caſe, were moved with the ſpectacle &amp; chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their minds, &amp; beſought the Emperour to keep his Crown, and promiſed for their parts to be quiet: yet do not you ſo, till your King ſhall performe all your demands.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:112413:12"/>
From that which hath been done by you,<note place="margin">5.6.</note> and repeated by me, I ſee other two errours baniſhed, which I conjoyn for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities ſake, leſt my Epiſtle ſhould encreaſe to a Treatiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That the King is no more to be <hi>Preſident,</hi> nor <hi>ſupreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall. It is the folly of your Divines, to make the Moderator of your Aſſemblies to be unto the <hi>King</hi> or his <hi>Delegate</hi> in Aſſemblies, as the <hi>Chancelor</hi> in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to the <hi>King,</hi> or his <hi>Deputy</hi> in Parliaments. But I extoll your courage, who now conclude with us,<note place="margin">Bellarmin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Ad Regium officium pertinet, ut legibus &amp; edict is ſuis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am fidem teneri, quam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes tenendam docent, &amp;c.</hi> Its the duty of Kings, by their Lawes &amp; Edicts to cauſe that faith to be kept, which the Prieſts teach ſhould bee kept. For <hi>the ſpirit of the Prophets is ſubject to the Prophets.</hi> But is <hi>Saul</hi> alſo among the Prophets? Is it true that the <hi>Anticovenanter</hi> ſayes, that in your Eccleſiaſticall judicatories, called 1 Seſſions, 2 Presbyterles, and 3 Synods, there wil be in the firſt, ſometimes twelve, ſometimes ſixteene, in ſome places 24. <hi>Lay-Elders</hi> for one <hi>Prieſt?</hi> Secondly, in your Presbyteries, Lay-elders of <hi>equal power and number?</hi> Thirdly, in your Synods as many <hi>Lay-elders</hi> with their Aſſeſſors as there is Prieſts; all which Lay-elders have as great power in matters of Doctrine and Diſcipline as the Prieſts themſelves, to <hi>judge,</hi> and paſſe <hi>Definitive ſentence?</hi> &amp;c. But I truſt it is not ſo, for I heare that they are offended to be called <hi>Lay-elders,</hi> and will be called <hi>Ruling-elders,</hi> and Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and ſo I doubt not but they have received <hi>orders</hi> from you. And therefore ſeeing Eccleſiaſticall perſons among you, have the managing of Church-affaires, the civil Magiſtrate muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to execute what you decree; neither ought he to judge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then you judge; neither can he hinder you to make Lawes in the Church. For, as <hi>Stapleton</hi> ſayes very learnedly with you, <hi>Oves non poſſunt judicare paſtores.</hi> Let the ſheep-heards judge of the ſheep, who muſt follow them; as Chriſts ſheep heard his voyce and followed him. Therefore you have moſt valiantly ſhaken off that yoke of the Kings <hi>ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie</hi> in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Novemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 29. 1638. <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t in Juhi</hi> 1638 5 5.</note> and at the Croſſe of <hi>Glaſgow</hi> proclaimed to the world (againſt the Kings Proclamation for raiſing the Aſſembly) that <hi>your Aſſemblies are the ſupreme
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112413:13"/>judicaterie in all cauſes eccleſiaſticall;</hi> and ſince ſupreme, its <hi>independent</hi> from the King,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> appeale from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3.</note> and your reaſon is good: for that which is ſuperiour cannot be ſubject to that which is inferiour. Now (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alſo ſayes) <hi>Regimen Eccleſiasticum ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limius eſt Politico.</hi> The Eccleſiaſticke government is higher then the Politicke: for <hi>Principatus politieus inſtitutus eſt ab hominibus, &amp; de jure gentium: at principatus eccleſiasticus eſt à ſolo Deo, &amp; de jure divino.</hi> The Politicke Government is inſtitute by men, and of the Law of Nations: but the Church Government is from God alone, and of Divine inſtitution. <q>Therefore you conclude right, that the king hath no more power to appoint officers in the Church, then you have power to appoint officers of ſtate for his Court.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Zions Plea,</hi> pag. 289. You anſwer well to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants objection, thus: If any object the Magiſtrates inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed anthority, it's quickly anſwered, <hi>That his power is not to weaken any ordinance of God, but for guarding and making good all Gods ordinances with the Sword.</hi> And in your prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> 18. <hi>December,</hi> 1638. you bring from your Booke of Diſcipline, a full and perfect deſcription of the Kings authority in Church matters, which is this, <hi>To aſsiſt and maintaine the diſcipline of the Kirk and puniſh them civilly who will not obey the cenſures thereof.</hi> And in your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Hamilton</hi> his Declaration, you ſay, <hi>That the Supreme Magiſtrate, as a Son of the Kirke, ought to receive the true meaning of the Kirke and cauſe it to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by thoſe whom God hath ſubjected unto him.</hi> Yea, it is ſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rre from being a prerogative due to the Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to bee Supreme governour in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, that it is a favour granted unto him to have any precedencie in Synods without voycing, (except hee would become a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elder, and have accommiſſion to come.) Therefore, it is moſt remarkable which you ſay in your Proteſtation 29. <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem.</hi> 1638. at <hi>Glaſgow.</hi> 
               <q>After 39 <hi>Nationall Aſſemblies</hi> of this Nationall Church, where neither the Kings Majeſty, nor any in his name was preſent: At the humble and earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the Aſſembly, His Majeſty graciouſly vouchſafed His preſence either in His owne Royall perſon, or by a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112413:13"/>not for voiting or mukiplying of voyces; but as Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Emperours of old, in a Princely manner to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance that meeting, and to preſide into it for externall order, &amp;c.</q> And this is all that wee grant to Emperors and Princes in our Diſputes againſt Proteſtants. And I pray you, what Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſt can anſwer the Arguments which you have borrowed from us? all their anſwer is, that they exclaime that you do borrow your Arguments from your enemies, yet not ſo great enemies, as they ſuppoſe; for the Jeſuite is called the Popiſh Puritan: and the Puritan is called the Proteſtant Jeſuite; and I truſt that the like may be ſaid of us, which is ſaid of Chriſt and <hi>Franciſcus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Turſ. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Exue Franciſcum tunica, lacero<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cucullo</l>
               <l>Qui Franciſcus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rat, jam tibi Chriſtus erit,</l>
               <l>Franciſci exuviis, ſi qua licet, indue Christum,</l>
               <l>Jam Franciſcus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit, qui tibi Chriſtus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And wee are both by Papiſts and Proteſtants (though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly) branded with theſe vile Epithers,<note place="margin">Ludav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>zam.</note> to bee called <hi>Holy Divels, the Standard-bearers of perſidionſneſſe, the Architypes of Rebellion, the Bellows of Sedition, the Emiſſaries of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, the Kings evill, and the Incendiaries of the whole world,</hi> &amp;c. and our <hi>Thuan</hi> is ſo farre out of Love with us, that hee ſayes our Societie is,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nata Magistratum convellere, nata miniſtris</l>
               <l>Subtrahere obſequium, Praeſulibuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But albeit there were ſome od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> between us, what is that to them, ſince they bee good for you? who found fault with him who ſaid,
<q>
                  <l>Mutemus clypeos, Danaum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> inſignia nobis</l>
                  <l>Aptimus, Dolus an virtus quis in hoſte requirat?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Who can blame you while you ſay,<note place="margin">Proteſtat. 18 Novem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 1638.</note> that if Princes ſhall have ſuch power in Aſſemblies, and in matters of Religion, then all <hi>Religion and Church-government ſhould depend abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely upon the pleaſure of the Prince.</hi> and hee may change it as he will? So ſayes learned <hi>Stapleton</hi> in his diſpute againſt the Proteſtant Doctrine: <hi>Poſita hac poteſtate, nec in una pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincia velregno din erit fidei unitas vel cultus, &amp; religionis conformitas, quia finguli principes quod ipſis melius videbitur, flatuent, quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> decretis ſiro ſiſtatur, perpetua erunt beſla.</hi> This power being granted to Kings, then Unitie of faith and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112413:14"/>and conformity of religion will not remaine lorg in one province or kingdome, becauſe every Prince will ordaine that which ſee meth beſt in his eyes. To whoſe decrees if reſiſtance be made, there will follow perpetuall warre. But this power being granted to the Church, which cannot erre in her Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall acts, there ſhall ever be Unity of faith depending upon the <hi>infallibility</hi> of Church Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> For I ſee in the ſeventh place, that you do acknowledge the <hi>infallibilitie</hi> of generall Councels or Aſſemblies. For that Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly which you did hold at <hi>Glaſgow</hi> lately,<note place="margin">Covenanters in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>at for De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nſive § 7.</note> is to you ſo <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible,</hi> that long time before, you doe profeſſe that you did <hi>ſwear for judgement and practice to adhere to the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it:</hi> And now of late, <hi>Julii</hi> 1. 1639 do <hi>proteſt before God and the world, that you will ſtill adhere to it.</hi> And you have good reaſon ſo to do: for if generall Aſſemblies may erre, then, ſay we,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. or. Cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Poſſent merito revocari in dubium omnes damnatae ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſes, &amp; concilia nullo honore digna eſſent.</hi> All hereſies which are condemned, may againe be called in queſtion, and our Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies eſteemed worthy of no honour. And therefore you may juſtly feare, upon this ground, that your Aſſembly might erre, and that you may be branded with errour in your decrees, and have all called in queſtion again which you have condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. As for us of Rome, condemne your Aſſemblies who will, we ſhall never doe it: but rather deſire that you may ſtill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the <hi>ſame Commiſſioners</hi> for your future aſſemblies, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to confirme all which they had decreed in the former: for your acts of abjuring <hi>Epiſcopacie,</hi> the <hi>Articles of Perth, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice book, Book of Canons,</hi> pleaſeth us very well: howbeit we doe not throughly approve the reaſon of your acts. You have thruſt away and excommunicated your Biſhops, becauſe you think them <hi>Antichriſtian:</hi> ſo doe we excommunicate your Biſhops, becauſe they are <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi> But you think them <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> becauſe you make it an Article of your <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faith,</hi> that they are a part of the <hi>Popiſh Hierarchie:</hi> And we thinke them <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> becauſe they are not ſo, neither doe they acknowledge the Pope for their Head, but doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime againſt him, and the greateſt wound that ever we have received, is from ſuch Biſhops as they are, as <hi>Cranmet, Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112413:14"/>Ridley, Hooper, Jowell, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſon, Andrewes</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſtupor mundi; <hi>Whitgift, Babington, Abbots, King, Downame, Uſſher, Morton, Davenant, Montague, Hall, White,</hi> and that Arch-enemie of yours and ours <hi>Canterbury,</hi> with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom I like not to recite.</p>
            <p>In this particular, King <hi>James</hi> is oppoſite to us both, becauſe (<hi>as Becanus</hi> well obſerveth) he holdeth,<note place="margin">Recan. de prim. Reg. Angl. ca. <hi>7.</hi> Jacobi Regis praeſa. monit.</note> that Biſhops have their juriſdiction immediately from God, while he ſaith, <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopos eſſe in Eccleſia debere, tanquam inſtitutionem Apostoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, ac ordinationem proinde divinam contra Puritanos, contra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Bollarminum ſemper ſenſi, qui negat Epiſcopos à Deo immediatè ſuam juriſdictionem accepiſſe. Sed nihil mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, à Puritanis cum ſtare, cum Jeſuitae nihil aliud quàm Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritano-papiſtae ſunt.</hi> I ever thought that Biſhops ought to bee in the Church, as an Apoſtolicall inſtitution, and therefore a divine ordinance againſt <hi>Puritans,</hi> and againſt <hi>Bellarmine;</hi> who deny that Biſhops have their jurisdiction immediately from God; but no marvell that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> takes the <hi>Puritans</hi> part, ſeeing <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are no other thing but <hi>Puritan-papiſts.</hi> And in that ſame place, the King ſheweth that from a generall Councell convocated by Chriſtian Princes, for the ſettling of Religion, he would have <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> excluded, whom he calleth by a common title <hi>novitios, &amp; furioſos incendiarios:</hi> and ſayes,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Mihi praecipuus labor fuit dejectos Epiſcopos reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuere, &amp; Puritanorum anarchiam expugnare.</hi> My chief labour was to reſtore the Biſhops that were caſt downe, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the anarchie of Puritans.</p>
            <p>Wee thanke you alſo for removing the Articles of <hi>Perth;</hi> for they were not rightly eſtabliſhed: for your Church did eſteeme thoſe ceremonies to be onely <hi>things indifferent,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and commanded by Authoritie, for <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order.</hi> The not obſervation whereof was held no <hi>damnable ſinne,</hi> if it were without <hi>contempt</hi> of Authority, and without the <hi>caſe of ſcandall;</hi> and at the moſt, your Church did hold that thoſe ceremonies were onely <hi>ſignificant,</hi> and not <hi>opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> as we hold. But if they had been rightly eſtabliſhed, you ſhould have obſerved them as things <hi>neceſſary to ſalvation,</hi> and as parts of <hi>Gods worſhip,</hi> which under paine of <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:112413:15"/>ought to be performed, and that they are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gns <hi>operater,</hi> working <hi>grace</hi> in thoſe who obſerve them. And therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Church did not hold this opinion of them, they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not <hi>Popiſh Ceremonies,</hi> and ſo not <hi>ours;</hi> and whatſoever you have more, that is not <hi>ours,</hi> we requeſt you to abjure it.</p>
            <p>The condemning alſo of the <hi>Service-book</hi> is moſt acceptable unto us, becauſe it is not our <hi>Maſſe-book;</hi> and that you may ſee how much we hate it, Be it known to you, that by venue of the Popes Bull many yeers agoe we will ſuffer no Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike to goe to the Church, ſo long as the <hi>Service-booke</hi> is reading either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> and yet we will permit them to goe to their Sermons, and of all Sermons we ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize beſt with yours: So that it ſeemeth a moſt unfortunate booke, having both us and you for its enemies.</p>
            <p>And ſince I am fallen upon this point, let me relate an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie that paſſed between a <hi>Covenanter</hi> &amp; an <hi>Anticovenanter,</hi> as it was reported to me, concerning this booke, that you may make y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur uſe of it. <q>The <hi>Covenanter</hi> demanded the cauſe, why he could refuſe to joyne with them in a Supplication to his Majeſtie againſt the book of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> ſeeing there were ſo many hands of able Miniſters ſubſcribing the ſame, and obliging themſelves to make it good, that it was 1. <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious.</hi> 2. <hi>that it conteineth the maine eſſentiall parts of the Maſſe.</hi> 3. <hi>that it openeth a doore to let in all Poperie?</hi> The <hi>Anticovenanter</hi> anſwered thus, or to this effect: Becauſe ſuch unjuſt aſperſions are caſt upon that poore Book, which doth not containe ſo many <hi>Lines,</hi> as it doth ſuffer <hi>Lyes,</hi> hated be all that love not truth; <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> ſtriving who ſhall ſpeake moſt againſt it, I ſhall bee ſo farre from becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a cauſleſſe enemy to it, that I cannot deny it my friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and helping hand. But becauſe you are ſo furious, and I for ſpeaking but one word in its favour have beene hotly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted with tongues, and hands too; it will be better to be poſſeſſed with a <hi>Lethargie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> then to appeare in defence of this <hi>Lyturgie,</hi> which the moſt part, even of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, hath condemned with blind obedience, before they did <hi>ſee</hi> or <hi>read</hi> it. It might be ſufficient for me to deny what you peremptorily affirme againſt it, and its your part to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112413:15"/>prove the <hi>Affirmative:</hi> and your beſt <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bation</hi> is your naked <hi>aſſertion,</hi> ſeconded with <hi>railing</hi> againſt all that will not beleeve you. But I pray you heare the Book ſpeak for it ſelfe, and it ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urge i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elfe of ſuch calumnies, in the judgement of all indifferent men, and it will tell you that you are like <hi>Davids</hi> enemies, caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing iniquitie upon it where you find none, and laying to its charge the thing it never knew, and ſo doe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it without a cauſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt then, here it purgeth it ſelfe of all Superſtition, at the <q> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt entrie of the booke, where it ſheweth the <hi>reaſons why ſome ceremonies are aboliſhed, and ſome retained,</hi> in plaine words, ſaying: <hi>The multitude of ceremonies are rejected, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their multitude and ſuperſtition.</hi> And in the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Holy Communion, it recommends the uſe of common bread. But wherefore? <hi>for the avoyding of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition,</hi> ſayes the booke; ſo that at the very entry, the booke is moſt carefull to ſatisfie all ſcrupulous people, thus telling them that it hates ſuperſtiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n as well as they. Again, if there were any thing ſuperſtitions in this booke, it muſt be enjoyned as a thing <hi>neceſſary in it ſelfe,</hi> as <hi>unchangeable;</hi> the not obſerving of it would be <hi>damnable,</hi> as the breach of <hi>Gods Law.</hi> To all this the Book anſwers in the ſame place, that it <hi>enjoyneth nothing in that manner but what the Word of God commands.</hi> And as for the ceremonies contained in it, it is ſo farre from eſteeming them <hi>things neceſſarie,</hi> that it placeth them in the ranke of <hi>indifferent things.</hi> The <hi>keeping or omitting whereof is but a ſmall thing,</hi> ſayes the booke: It ſayes further, that <hi>thoſe ceremonies are taken away which were moſt abuſed, and did burthen m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns conſciences without cauſe, and that thoſe which remain are retained for diſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and order.</hi> It tells that they are alſo <hi>changeable,</hi> and not to bee compared to <hi>Gods Law,</hi> whileſt it ſayes of them thus, <hi>Upon juſt cauſes they may be alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red and changed, and therefore are not to bee eſteemed equall with Gods Law.</hi> What can any man ſay more againſt ſuperſtition then is ſaid by the book it ſelf? Therefore, its very likely that they have not read the book, (as I am ſure the moſt part have never done) or at leaſt, have read it with an <hi>evilleye;</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112413:16"/>it of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> whereof it is moſt free.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>
               <q>As for the ſecond, that it doth containe the <hi>eſſentiall parts of the Maſſe,</hi> read and ſee the contrary in the book it ſelfe, which doth keepe Chriſts <hi>inſtitution it ſelfe,</hi> and <hi>Pauls re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of it,</hi> in ſuch ſort, that I thinke no Church can cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Sacrament with more <hi>puritie, ſinceritie, gravitie,</hi> and none with more <hi>Majeſtie</hi> then by this booke. But let me ſpeak a little for it. I pray you, Why are you ſo ſparing? you may ſay as well, that it containes the <hi>whole Maſſe,</hi> as the <hi>maine eſſentiall parts of the Maſſe;</hi> for (if you have any Logicke, or naturall reaſon) you may ſo conclude: for where that is, which is eſſentiall to a thing, there the thing it ſelfe muſt be: But in this booke (ſay you) <hi>are the eſſentiall parts of the Maſſe,</hi> what doth hinder then, but that it hath the Maſſe it ſelfe in it? for, if it have the maine eſſentiall parts of the Maſſe, what doth it lack or want? not the <hi>proper accidents,</hi> for theſe do flow from <hi>the eſſentiall parts,</hi> and are <hi>inſeparable</hi> from it. It can want nothing then of the Maſſe, unleſſe it be <hi>ſome common accidents,</hi> which may be either <hi>preſent</hi> or <hi>abſent,</hi> without any hurt of the <hi>ſubject.</hi> What boldneſſe is this then to ſpeak ſuch a maine eſſentiall lye? Let me either ſee that the book maintaineth, that, <hi>ſub ſpeciebus panis &amp; vini,</hi> the body and bloud of Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>bodily offered up</hi> by the Prieſt, to God the Father, a <hi>propitiatory ſacrifice for the quick and the dead;</hi> or elſe, lay your hand on your mouth, &amp; ſpeak no more.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/>
               <q>Finally, ſince it hath neither <hi>Superſtition,</hi> not the <hi>eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of the Maſſe,</hi> how can it <hi>open a doore to Popery?</hi> certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is purged from all ſuch ſtuffe, and reſtored to the antient integritie, the leaſt thing that might tend to <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thruſt out of doore, as <hi>Ammon</hi> did <hi>Tamar, without hope of return:</hi> and if any ſuperſtition would dare to enter, as the Sodomits at <hi>Lots</hi> doore, <hi>the doore is ſo fast ſhut</hi> (by that which I have told you from the mouth of the book it ſelfe, in the beginning of the right uſe and abuſe of Ceremonies) that they muſt deſpaire of any entrie.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>What needs all ſuch uproare then without cauſe? ſuch fearfull Schiſmes ſuch Dictatorial cenſures, and uncharitable verdicts, that they are all Papiſts, or Popiſhly affected,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112413:16"/>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un not with you to miſchiefe? Shew me but one <hi>maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line reaſon</hi> (and lay aſide wives tales) and I ſhall take it in place of many: <hi>&amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>runt ultimi primi,</hi> I ſhall redeeme my time with redoubling my courſe, and ſhall be ſo far from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the leaſt point, which you ſhall ſhew to be Poperie, that for that one points ſake, it ſhall get no more pitie then <hi>Samuel</hi> gave to <hi>Agag: I ſhall rent it in pieces.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q> Reade over that which you have condemned with judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not with prejudice, and I ſhall oblige my ſelfe to make good thoſe particulars: Firſt, that you ſhall never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to find any thing in it <hi>contrary to the word of God.</hi> 2. That it containeth nothing contrary to the practiſe of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, but which is moſt agreeable thereto. 3. That all the points which you condemne, are <hi>not controverted</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene our <hi>claſſicall Divines</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but agreed upon on <hi>both ſides,</hi> as things not <hi>controverted.</hi> 4. That there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it contrary to our Confeſſion of Faith in Scotland. Yea, which is much, you ſhall not ſhow me one Proteſtant Divine of any note or <hi>eminencie,</hi> even among the <hi>Reformers of Religion,</hi> who ever did condemne this booke of the leaſt <hi>point of Popery:</hi> But on the contrary did commend it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it againſt all pettie preachers who refuſed it, as you do. Learned <hi>Bucer</hi> thus affirmeth,<note place="margin">Bucer, Script. Angl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. in con. pag. <hi>456.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In the Ceremonies of the Engliſh L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>turgie, I have found nothing which is not taken out of the Word of God, or at leaſt, which is repugnant to it, ſo it be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably underſtood. Calvin</hi> himſelfe peruſing the <hi>Lyturgie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in epiſt. <hi>200.</hi> fol. <hi>336.</hi>
                  </note> declared that he found no fault in it at all; <hi>and wrote to the Engliſh Exiles at Frankford, who had made a rent and ſchiſme in the Church, to be moderate and returne to the Church Vos ultra modum rigidos eſſe nolim.</hi> I would not have you ſtiffe above meaſure; and bids them returne to Conformitie, and proponeth his owne opinion, <hi>in Anglorum controverſia moderationem ſemper tenni, cujus me non poenitet.</hi> In the controverſie of England I have ever kept a moderation, whereof I do not repent: and was very much offended with thoſe who would not <hi>yeeld</hi> in ſuch <hi>indifferent things,</hi> for peace ſake. It was <hi>Calvin</hi> with <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> who by many arguments perſwaded Biſhop <hi>Hooper</hi> to <hi>conformitie,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112413:17"/>to put on the <hi>Surpleſſe,</hi> which he did. I might produce all the reſt of thoſe worthy Divines, <hi>Beza, Melancton, Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Peter Martyr, Gualter, Zanchius,</hi> who all of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn your <hi>opinion</hi> &amp; <hi>ſchiſmaticall practice,</hi> who had rather rent the body of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> then yeeld to any thing that doth not content your turbulent luſts: and therefore your praiers are turned into ſin, while you <hi>pray the Lord of heaven truly and fully to inform his Majeſty how farre this Booke is full of idolatrous ſuperſtitions and popiſh errors,</hi> as you affirm in your Proteſtation againſt his Majeſties Proclamation. And it is no marvell that you condemne this <hi>Booke of Common Praier,</hi> ſeeing you have condemned your <hi>owne book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> Praier made at your <hi>Reformation.</hi> The Ring-leaders of your <hi>faction</hi> condemne all <hi>ſet Praier</hi> whatſoever, all <hi>ſet forme</hi> of celebration of the <hi>Sacraments</hi> &amp; <hi>Marriages.</hi> The praiers which were read ſince the Reformation till this rupture, are now baniſhed the Church, yea your Ring-leaders have bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the <hi>Lords Praier,</hi> and ſay that thoſe who uſe it make it an <hi>Idoll:</hi> and therefore in their praiers it is never mentioned, to the great ſcandall &amp; grief of many poor ſouls among you, who yet love it, becauſe Chriſts command is when you pray, ſay, <hi>Our Father which art in heaven, &amp;c.</hi> You <hi>Baptize,</hi> cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the <hi>Communion,</hi> not as you were wont to do after the <hi>form</hi> ſet downe unto you at the Reformation: but every day after a <hi>diverſe forme and manner,</hi> being <hi>changeable</hi> like the wind; ſo do you with <hi>Marriage.</hi> Thus you differ from <hi>your ſelfe</hi> like the <hi>double-minded man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>who is unſtable in all his waies; wavering like the waves of the ſea, driven with the wind, &amp; toſſed.</hi> And what pleaſeth you to day, diſpleaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th you to morrow. You do alſo daily coin <hi>new</hi> Articles of faith, as to beleeve <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> to be <hi>Antichriſtian:</hi> and the <hi>young Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elder</hi> government to be that which Chriſt hath appointed in his Church. It is an <hi>Article of your faith</hi> to beleeve, that to receive the body and bloud of Jeſus Chriſt, in the humble ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of <hi>kneeling</hi> is <hi>idolatry.</hi> It is an <hi>Article of your faith,</hi> that it is <hi>Popery,</hi> if the Church ſet apart <hi>a day</hi> for the ſolemn and thankfull commemoration of Gods love to the world, <hi>who ſo loved the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galat 4 4</note> 
                  <hi>that when the fulneſſe of time was
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112413:17"/>come, ſent forth his Sonne made of a woman, made under the Law, to redeem them which were under the Law; that wee might receive the adoption of Sons.</hi> It is an <hi>Article of your faith,</hi> that it is <hi>Popery,</hi> if the Church doth ſet apart <hi>a day</hi> for the ſolemne and publike commemoration of the <hi>Paſsion of Christ,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> that <hi>the people may looke unto Jeſus the Author and Finiſher of their faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him endured the croſſe, deſpiſing the ſhame.</hi> Its an <hi>Article of your faith,</hi> that it is <hi>Popery</hi> to give the Communion <hi>on Paſch day.</hi> Its an <hi>Article of your faith,</hi> that it is Popery, if the Church appoint <hi>a day</hi> for the thankfull remembrance of Chriſts <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion</hi> into Heaven. Its an <hi>Article of your faith,</hi> that its <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> if the Church appoint <hi>a day</hi> for the thankfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the <hi>Deſcenſion of the Holy Ghoſt</hi> on <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> to give gifts unto men. Its an <hi>Article of your faith,</hi> that the <hi>Service-book</hi> is <hi>Popiſh.</hi> Its an <hi>Article of your faith,</hi> that the <hi>Book of Canons</hi> (which directly overthrowes the Popiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie) and the <hi>High Commiſsion</hi> are <hi>abjured</hi> in your Confeſſion of faith. Its an <hi>Article of your faith,</hi> that it was the <hi>intention</hi> of thoſe whom you call <hi>bleſſed Reformers,</hi> that all the <hi>foreſaids,</hi> which you have in your Covenant <hi>abjured expreſly,</hi> was abjured by them alſo <hi>as well as if it had bin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſet downe:</hi> which is the moſt ridiculous thing in the world; for <hi>intentio est actus immanens,</hi> which is impoſſible for any man to know, except it be revealed. And therefore ſince there is ſuch difference among your ſelves, every day bringing forth new <hi>dreames,</hi> ſince to you ſome things are ſometimes <hi>indifferent,</hi> ſometimes <hi>neceſſary good,</hi> ſometimes <hi>neceſſary evill,</hi> ſometimes a matter <hi>of faith,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Not:</hi> I cannot but end this diſcourſe with that of <hi>Hilarius</hi> in Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to you.<note place="margin">Hilar. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cont. Conſtant.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith is come now to depend rather on the time then on the Goſpel: our ſtate is dangerous and miſerable, that we have now as many Faiths as wills, as many doctrines as manners. Whilſt Faiths are either ſo written as we liſt, or ſo underſtood as we will, we make every yeer &amp; every moneth a faith, and ſtill we ſeek a faith, as if there were no faith. This I would fain know of you, what faith at length you beleeve!you have changed ſo often, that now I know not your Faith. That
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112413:18"/>is happened unto you, which is wont to follow unskilfull buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ever diſliking their owne doings, that you ſtill put down that which you are ſtill putting up. You ſubvert the old with the new and the new you rent aſunder with a new correction: and that which was once corrected, you condemus with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond correction. O wicked men, what a mockery do you make of the Church! onely dogs returne to their vomit, and you compell the Prieſts to ſup up thoſe things which they have ſpit forth; and doe you command them in their confeſsion to allow that which before they condemned? What Biſhops hand have you left innocent? What tongue have you not forced to falſhood? Whoſe heart haſt thou not brought to the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his former opinion? You have ſubjected all to your will, and to your violence. Thus</hi> Hilarius.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And therefore of thoſe your <hi>new-coyned articles</hi> (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of your abjuring <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and eſtabliſhing <hi>Preſbyteriall diſcipline</hi>) I may wel ſay that of <hi>Jerom Plantatio veſtra non eſt vetus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jerom. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſed novella eſt; non eſt de veterilege, non de Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, non de Apoſtolis, ſed de novis magiſtris eſt.</hi> Your planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not old, but a novelty, (for it is not three yeers old) it is not taken out of the old Law, nor from the Prophets, nor from the Apoſtles, but new maſters. And therefore, <hi>adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt, impium eſt, ſacrilegum eſt, quicquid humano furere inſtituitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pr. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ut diſpoſitio divina violetur.</hi> Whatſoeuer is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the fury of man, whereby the divine diſpoſition is violated, is an adulterate, wicked &amp; ſacrilegious matter. And I hold that, as an undoubted rule of <hi>Auguſtine, Quod uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalis tenuit eccleſia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Bapt. cap. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quod<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> non Conciliis inſtitutum ſed ſemper retentum eſt, non niſi Apoſtolicâ authoritate traditum rectiſſimè creditur.</hi> Whatſoever the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> hath holden, &amp; which was not inſtitute by <hi>Councels,</hi> but ever kept in the Church, that is moſt rightly beleeved to be an <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall tradition:</hi> and he brings for inſtances thoſe <hi>holy daies,</hi> which your Covenant <hi>abjures,</hi> which hath ever been retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Church from the Apoſtles daies. And albeit we could not prove <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> from Scripture (as wee may very wel prove it, and is proved by thoſe who defend the ſame) yet this unqueſtionable rule of <hi>Augustine</hi> will bee ſufficient to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112413:18"/>prove it to be of <hi>Apoſtolicall inſtitution;</hi> for you ſay, it is not of <hi>Divine inſtitution,</hi> and I ſay, it is not inſtituted by <hi>Councels:</hi> and yet all that are but little exerciſed in <hi>antiquitie,</hi> ſhall find that <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> was ever in the Church from the Apoſtles dayes, till this preſent time that it is called in queſtion. And beſide that rule of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> conſider that it is the <hi>generall tradition</hi> of the <hi>Catholik Church,</hi> that <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> hath ever been in it, as an <hi>Apoſtolicall inſtitution.</hi> And by this <hi>generall tradition</hi> of the Catholike Church, we are as certain, that it is of <hi>Apoſtolicall institution,</hi> as we are certaine of the <hi>received number</hi> of the <hi>Canonicall books</hi> of Scripture: for we receive and take that number upon the <hi>continued, generall tradition</hi> of the Catholike Church of Chriſt from age to age. We reject and deteſt <hi>particular traditions</hi> of any <hi>preſent particular</hi> Church; ſuch as are thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if they cannot ſhew thoſe <hi>traditions</hi> to have been <hi>generally</hi> received <hi>at all times</hi> in the Catholike Church. But there is no Proteſtant that doth not receive <hi>generall traditions</hi> of the Catholike Church; ſuch as is this, concerning the <hi>definite number</hi> of the bookes of the Canonical Scripture: and if I would aſſume a ſchiſmaticall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, I might with as good warrants deny, that there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bookes in the <hi>Canon,</hi> as the Catholike Church ſayes there be; as you deny <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> to be of <hi>Apoſtolicall inſtitution.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> Thus have I briefly ſhowne you the paſſages betweene the <hi>Anticovenanter</hi> and <hi>Covenanter,</hi> which I leave to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and returne to my purpoſe. From this ſweet har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie in the preceding points, eſpecially of your <hi>indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent power</hi> in Church matters, there followeth another pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel by way of conſequence, <hi>viz.</hi> that you may excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate your King, if hee doe not obey the Acts and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of your Aſſemblies. Thus you threatned King <hi>James,</hi> and his Councell both, with excommunication, if he would not execute your Acts of your Aſſemblie; and good reaſon, ſeeing it is the <hi>ſupreme judicatory,</hi> and the King is a <hi>ſonne of your Church, from whom he ought to take the meaning.</hi> And if hee bee refractarie, why may not the Aſſembly excommunicate him, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>doſius?</hi> And as I have ſaid alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from your <hi>Travers,</hi> of your government, <hi>Huic diſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:112413:19"/>omnes Principes, &amp;c.</hi> There is a neceſſity that all Princes &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs ſhould ſubmit their Scepter, and obey this Diſcipline. Its your <hi>chief Commander in the Camproyall. Thomas Cartwright</hi> being asked, <hi>whether the King himſelf might be excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> anſwered, <hi>That excommunication ſhould not bee exerciſed upon Kings, I utterly miſlike:</hi> and ſo do we alſo; yea, albeit they be not Heretickes themſelves, yet if they doe not puniſh ſuch as their Paſtors commands them, they may be excommunicate. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ac debet Paſtor regibus jubere ut puniant Haereticos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. contra Barklaiun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c niſi fecerint, etiam cogere per excommunicationem.</hi> The Paſtor may, and ought to command Kings to puniſh Hereticks, &amp; if they do it not, even to compell them with excommunication. But eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, <hi>ſi ſit Haereticorum vel Schiſmaticorum fautor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. part. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>receptor, vel. defenſor;</hi> if hee be a favourer, receiver or defender of Hereticks and Schiſmaticks. If your Biſhops be ſuch men, is not this your Kings fault? your <hi>fault is, that you uſe but too much lenity,</hi> in not aſcending from the <hi>Myter</hi> to the <hi>Crown;</hi> for this may ſtand very well with your Tenent and Ours, though Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines diſclaim it: for your <hi>Buchanan</hi> teacheth you, that not only it is lawfull to <hi>excommunicate</hi> Princes, but that they ſhould both <hi>depoſe</hi> him,<note place="margin">Buchan. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure reg. apud Scot. pag. <hi>70.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>deſtroy</hi> him; for hee ſayes, <hi>Miniſters may excommunicate Princes, and he being by excommunication caſt into Hell, is not worthy to enjoy any life upon earth.</hi> But truly <hi>Knox</hi> &amp; <hi>Buchanan</hi> are more <hi>rigid</hi> then we are herein; for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, we grant that it's lawfull to excommunicate Kings, yet wee hold it not neceſſary that upon excommunication, either <hi>depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>killing.</hi> ſhould follow. Indeed by our common Tenent it will follow, that excommunication is an <hi>antecedent</hi> to depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or killing; but we do not hold that deprivation or killing of Princes is a neceſſary <hi>conſequent,</hi> or <hi>effect</hi> of excommunication. For (ſay we) <hi>quando talis effectus adjungitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ez. de cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. diſp. <hi>15.</hi> ſect. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non eſt effect us ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius excommunicationis, ſed ſpecialis poena ſimul cum excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatione impoſita.</hi> When ſuch an effect is joyned to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, its not the effect of it, but a ſpeciall puniſhment im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with it. But its wonderfull to ſee the wide difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this our Tenent and yours, and that which Proteſtants hold; for they make the power of the ſupreme Magiſtrate <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectonicke,</hi> and ſubject unto it, all power <hi>civill</hi> &amp; <hi>Eccleſiaſticall.</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:112413:19"/>So that, as in civill affaires they uſe the counſell and help of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians and Juriſconſults for eſtabliſhing of Lawes, according to <hi>reaſon;</hi> ſo in Eccleſiaſticall buſineſſe, they uſe the help and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of learned Divines for eſtabliſhing religion according to <hi>Gods Word,</hi> which ought never to depart from their hands. And its moſt boldly ſaid by them in the words of Biſhop <hi>Davenant, Reges non it a aſtringuntur Epiſcoporum vel Theologorum ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum opinionibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Daven. deter. quaſt. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quin ſi adverſentur legi divina (cujus oportet reges ſtudioſiſſimos &amp; peritiſsimos eſſe) teneantur ex officio re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio, veram religionem, illis omnibus licet reclamantibus, tueri, &amp; ſubditis ſuis proponere:</hi> Kings are not ſo tyed to the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Biſhops and Theologues, but if they bee contrary to the Law of God, (of the which Kings ought to be great ſtudiers, and very well skilled) they are bound by <hi>their Kingly Office</hi> to defend the true religion, and ſet it before their Subjects, albeit all thoſe Divines ſhould cry out againſt it. But thoſe men are <hi>Court Paraſites,</hi> as your uſuall word is; or as <hi>Beeanus</hi> calls thoſe that defend the Kings Supremacie, <hi>regios adulatores,</hi> King-flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers. And I admire that <hi>Tertullian</hi> being under Heathen Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours ſhould be guilty of thoſe flatteries, while hee ſayes in a Court-like complement, <hi>Reges in ſolius Deipoteſtate ſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Terſul. ad Scap.</note> 
               <hi>à quo ſunt ſecunds, poſt quem primi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ante omnes, &amp; ſuper omnes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s &amp; homines:</hi> Kings are only in the power of God, from whom they are ſecond, after whom they are firſt, before all, and above all gods and men. But I like not to trouble my ſelfe with ſuch men, but proceed to another head.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IX"/> Which is concerning the power of your Diſcipline in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things, wherein is a queſtion whether our, or your diſcipline, <hi>the chiefe Commander in the Camp royall,</hi> have the greateſt power. You do learnedly hold,<note place="margin">Anſwer to the Marqueſs <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millons</hi> Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> that the Kings high Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>cannot hinder you to make Lawes Eccleſiaſticall, ſeeing your Eccleſiaſticall government is independent.</hi> Yea, you doe hold, that your Aſſemblies may <hi>repeal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>adnull,</hi> even the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall lawes that are <hi>confirmed</hi> in Parliament, ſo that upon your re-calling them, the <hi>ſanction</hi> of the Parliament is <hi>nullita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and of no <hi>effect.</hi> Your own words are Emphaticall:<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Albeit acts of generall Aſſemblies b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ratified in Parliament, yet a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly may re-call thoſe confirmed acts, which being
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112413:20"/>adnulled, the civil ratification and ſanction falls ex conſequenti.</hi> Certainely, I dare promiſe you the Popes bleſſing for this moſt learned <hi>Theſis:</hi> for now a <hi>door is opened to let in all Popery,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King will or no; ſo that I truſt (as I ſaid at the beginning) our Union ſhalbe full. For ſince your Aſſemblies have ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over Parliaments, as to <hi>adnull all eccleſiaſticall lawes confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med therein</hi> (as you have done already with Epiſcopacy and the articles of <hi>Perth,</hi> which ſtand ratified and confirmed by divers acts of Parliament) then it ſhal be eaſie for you at any Aſſembly, when or where you wil, to <hi>repeal</hi> and <hi>adnull</hi> all the eccleſiaſticall lawes <hi>ratified</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> by <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> in favour of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion:</hi> and to eſtabliſh new lawes for our Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Religion in ſtead of it, though the <hi>King, Parliament and Councell</hi> ſhould reſiſt you. You haue good reaſon for it: for as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lericis, lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Habet ſe poteſtas eccleſiaſtica ad ſecularem, quomodo Spiritus ſe habet ad carnem, quam regit, moderatur, &amp; aliquando cohibet. Caro autem nullum habet imperium inſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illum ulla in re dirigere, vel judicare, vel coercere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Sic igitur poteſtas eccleſiaſtica, quae ſpiritualis eſt, as per hoc naturaliter ſeculari ſuperior, ſecularem poteſtatem cum opu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt, dirigere, judicare, &amp; coercere poteſt, ipſam verò à ſeculari di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigi vel coorceri nullâratione permittitur.</hi> The <hi>eccleſiaſticall power</hi> is to the <hi>ſecular power,</hi> as the <hi>ſpirit</hi> is to the <hi>fleſh;</hi> which rules, moderates, and ſometimes reſtrains. But the <hi>fleſh</hi> hath no command over the <hi>ſpirit:</hi> neither can it direct, or judge, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain it in any thing. So then the <hi>eccleſiaſticall power</hi> which is ſpirituall, and therefore naturally <hi>ſuperiour</hi> to the <hi>ſecular,</hi> may <hi>direct, judge,</hi> and <hi>reſtrain</hi> the ſecular power when it is needfull. But by no reaſon is it permitted to bee <hi>directed</hi> or <hi>reſtrained</hi> by the <hi>ſecular power:</hi> and therefore when your King did by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation diſcharge your Aſſembly at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> which ought to <hi>direct him,</hi> and not bee <hi>cohibited</hi> or <hi>reſtrained</hi> by him, you did well to ſit ſtill, and <hi>adnull</hi> divers acts of Parliament. And in your <hi>Proteſtation</hi> againſt the Kings Proclamation for raiſing your Aſſembly,<note place="margin">Proteſtat. Novemb. 29. 1638.</note> as it was your wiſdome not to enter into <hi>direct</hi> action with his Majeſty, ſo it was your courage, <hi>to ſummon all the Lords of his Majeſties Councel who conſented to the Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to appear before the Parliament the</hi> 25 <hi>of May,</hi> 1639. There
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112413:20"/>to be puniſhed for giving the King <hi>evill councell,</hi> viz <hi>to raiſe the Aſſemblies.</hi> When the K. commands one thing by <hi>acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> or by his <hi>Proclamations,</hi> you may <hi>proteſt</hi> againſt the ſame, and <hi>command</hi> the contrary in your <hi>proteſtations</hi> and <hi>acts of Aſſemblie:</hi> for as we ſay well,<note place="margin">Autor. lib. ad perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Angl. fol. <hi>336.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>et eccleſia prapoſites facultas eſt ampliſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a interdicendi nobis, ne reges obedient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>â &amp; abſequio neſtre honoremus.</hi> Theſe that are ſet over us in the Church have a very large power given them, even to interdict us, that we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour not our Ks. with our obedience. So the Councell of Trent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands all to receive the decr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> without regard to their <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces conſent,</hi> and denounceth <hi>ex communication</hi> in caſe of refuſall, requires an <hi>oath of obedience,</hi> approveth <hi>violence</hi> in rooting out of hereſie, &amp; ordains the Inquiſition for them. Therfore when the King by his <hi>Proclamation</hi> did <hi>command</hi> that the <hi>Covenant</hi> of K. <hi>James</hi> as it was in 1581. yeer of God, ſhould be ſubſcribed, you by <hi>your authority</hi> did <hi>prohibite</hi> any to ſubſcribe it, but will have <hi>your own</hi> ſubſcribed. For this cauſe in your <hi>general Aſſembly</hi> you have ſet down <hi>An act diſcharging ſubſcription to the Covenant which was ſubſcribed by the Kings Commiſsioner and Lords of the Councell;</hi> which his Majeſty, in his marginall note, calls <hi>a traitorous act.</hi> You have another excellent Act, <hi>diſcharging all Printers in Scotland to print any thing in Eccleſiaſticall affaires without the warrant of</hi> Jhonſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on <hi>your Clerk</hi> You have Acts alſo concerning <hi>mills, ſalt pans, and market dayes on Munday and Saturday.</hi> And eſpecially your Aſſembly hath adnulled his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>Court of high Commiſsion:</hi> all this we ſee in the <hi>Index</hi> of your Acts, &amp; all is well done, though it encroach upon the <hi>civill power:</hi> for <hi>in temperalibus Eccleſia non ſolù<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> praecipit, dirigit,<note place="margin">Odoard. VVeſt. in Sanctu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Pontiſ <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.6.</hi>
                  </note> ſed coercet, diſponit, virtute potestatit gubernativa.</hi> In temporall things the Church not only <hi>commands</hi> &amp; <hi>directs,</hi> but <hi>reſtrains</hi> &amp; diſpones by vertue of her <hi>gubernative power.</hi> And you know we do not maintain a <hi>direct</hi> power in <hi>temporall things,</hi> but an <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect</hi> power <hi>in ordius ad ſpiritualia;</hi> for we ſtand not upon <hi>words,</hi> when we are ſure of the <hi>matter it ſelf,</hi> and may bring all <hi>tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> within the compaſſe of <hi>our power.</hi> But I pray you, why did you forget to adnull the Acts of Parliament that doe ratifie the Kings <hi>Supremacy,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>ſpirituall things?</hi> ſince you have adnulled other Acts of Parliament, why have you prejudged
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112413:21"/>your ſelves ſo much as to leave thoſe acts for <hi>Supremacie</hi> uncan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled? If you had remembred the complaint of your holy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in former times, you would not have forgotten this, but as you have <hi>de facto,</hi> taken it away, ſo <hi>de jure,</hi> you would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the ſame an <hi>unlawfull act:</hi> for (as your predeceſſors ſaid) If the King have <hi>ſupreme power in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thinus</hi> additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Holin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,</hi> pag 446.</note> 
               <hi>then there is nothing left of the whole antient forme of Juſtices and policies in the ſpirituall eſtate, but a naked ſhadow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> I goe on to a tenth Parallel, which is your <hi>diſpenſation with oaths,</hi> even with the <hi>oath of Allegeance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> &amp; with the <hi>oath of Canonicall obedience.</hi> You will not upbraid us again with this, as if we were only <hi>enemies</hi> and <hi>traiters</hi> to Kings: For we diſpence with no Subjects oath of Allegeance, ſo long as they defend the religion; but if they either fall from the religion themſelves, or will not defend it by the civill ſword, wee doe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ſubjects of their <hi>oath of Allegeance,</hi> as wee did in the <hi>holy League</hi> of France, tying all to us by covenant very like unto yours, and in the end, took up armes againſt the King: for Kings fall from their authority, when they fall from religion, as you ſay in your Covenant: <hi>The Kings authority and true religion are ſo ſtrictly joyned together, that they ſtand and fall together.</hi> And therefore you do well to limit your obedience unto him, ſo long as he <hi>defends the Religion and Lawes,</hi> wherein if hee faile, by oath of Covenant you have made a <hi>mutuall band of defence againſt him,</hi> ſo that what is <hi>done to the leaſt of you, ſhall be done to you all in generall and particular.</hi> And ſo, if he ſhall doe any harme to the meaneſt <hi>Kitchin boy,</hi> you are all in generall &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular bound to take his part againſt your King. Now all this could not bee lawfully done, without a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> and <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> from your oath of Allegeance taken long before the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Our enemies ſay, that they who thus being abſolved from their <hi>oath of Allegeance,</hi> doe take up armes againſt <hi>their Prince,</hi> will have ſuch ſucceſſe in the end as <hi>Radulphus</hi> Duke of Swevia (whom Gregorie the ſeventh abſolved from his oath of Allegeance to <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth the Emperor,) received in battel againſt the Emperour, and hopes that they ſhall make the like confeſſion as he did.<note place="margin">He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mold in Chron Sla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. cap. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> For he being deadly wounded in the right hand, ſaid to his company, <hi>You ſee how my right hand is ſore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112413:21"/>of a hurt, it is the hand whereby I ſware to my Lord and Maſter, that I would never annoy him, that J would never lye in ambuſh to intercept his glory: but the Popes commands brought me to this, to breake my Oath, and uſurpe an honour which was not due to me. You ſee, what end it is come to, J have received this mortall wound upon the hand that brake this Oath. Let them then who have inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us to do ſo, conſider in what manner they urged us, for feare that we be not brought to the downefall of damnation,</hi> &amp;c. But be not you <hi>troubled nor afraid of ſhadowes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenanters inform. for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive. §. 4. &amp; 2.</note> 
               <hi>But let unity be earneſtly recommended, as that which ſtrengthens the cauſe, and will make you invincible.</hi> Your ſucceſſe hath been great hitherto, ſo that you may <hi>have confidence for the time to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have alſo diſpenſed with the Oath of <hi>Canonicall obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience:</hi> for I cannot thinke that you would exact of your Clergie the Oath of <hi>your Covenant,</hi> except you did firſt give them a diſpenſation for their former Oathes. For all have ſworne the Oath of Canonicall Obedience, ſome once, ſome thrice, and all admitted ſince the yeare 1618. had ſworne to <hi>Perths</hi> Articles, and preſent government of the Church, and now have taken the direct contradictory Oath, and <hi>abjured them all.</hi> And therefore it was not ill adviſed by you, to make an Act in your generall Aſſembly at <hi>Glaſgow, Novemb.</hi> 1638. <hi>declaring the nullity of the Oath exacted by Prelates of intrants, and of their bonds of Conformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here I muſt tell you, that you are gone a little beyond us in your diſpenſation with the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> to your King, and taking the <hi>Oath of mutuall defence</hi> againſt him: for according to our practiſe, you ought by all meanes endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to recall him from his errours, and being <hi>obſtinate,</hi> then to excommunicate him: for as our <hi>Tolet</hi> ſayes well, <hi>Licet ſit notorium crimen principis, non abſolvuntur vaſalli à juramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to (ut bene dicit Cajemnus) ante denunciationem ab Eccleſia: quâ factà, non ſolùm ſunt abſoluti ab obedientia, ſed tenentur non obedire, niſi forte propter periculum vitae, vel damnum bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum temporalium.</hi> Albeit the crime of the Prince be notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yet the Vaſſals are not abſolved from their Oath (as <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetan</hi> ſayes well) before the ſentence be denounced by the Church: which being done, they are not only abſolved from
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112413:22"/>obedience, but alſo are bound not to obey, except perchance for danger of their life, or loſſe of temporall goods. And <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel Sa</hi> ſayes the ſame.<note place="margin">Emanuel Sa in voce Tyrannus.</note> 
               <hi>Tyrannicè gubernans, juſtè acquiſito Dominio non poteſt ſpoliari ſine publico judicio: latâ verò ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentià, poteſt quiſque fieri executor. Poteſt autem deponi à po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo etiam qui illi juraverat obedientiam perpetuam, ſi monitus, non vult corrigi.</hi> A Tyrant that ruleth tyrannically, cannot have his juſtly acquired Dominion taken from him, without publike judgement: but the ſentence being given, any man may be the executioner, and he may be depoſed by the people who have ſworne perpetuall obedience unto him, if after ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition he will not be amended. And then it followeth clearely which <hi>Suarez</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Suarez lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si ſubditi juramento ſoluti ſunt, quamvis rex ille proditionem vocet, omniſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> regni aut reipublica conſpirationem, revera tamen talis non eſt, ſed juſta defenſie, vel juſtum bellum, ſeu ſupplicium.</hi> If the Subjects be abſolved from their oath, albeit that the King call it treaſon, and a conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of all the Kingdome and Common-wealth, yet certainly, it is no ſuch thing, but a juſt defence, or juſt warre, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
            <p>But I muſt crave your pardon for ſaying, that you went beyond us; for there are ſome of us as hot-blouded as your ſelves. <hi>De fide certum eſt quemcunque Principem Christi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um, ſi à Religione catholica deflexerit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philopat.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 109.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; alios avocare voluerit, excidere ſtatim omni poteſtate &amp; dignitate, id<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ante prolatam Papa ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam: poſſéque &amp; debere ſubditos, ſi vires habeaut, iſtinſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> Hareticum ex hominum Chriſtianorum dominatu ejicere.</hi> It is certainly a matter of Faith, that whatſoever Chriſtian Prince ſhall depart from the Catholike religion, and ſhall withdraw others, doth immediately fall from all power and dignity, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before the Popes ſentence be given; and that the Subjects may, and ſhould (if they have ſtrength) caſt forth ſuch an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick from the dominion of Chriſtian men. To this purpoſe, your Reformer <hi>Knox</hi> ſayes well.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Knox</hi> to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland and Scotland, fol. 78.</note> 
               <hi>If Princes be Tyrants againſt God and his Truth, their Subjects are free from their Oath of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi> And in his Hiſtory of Scotland, <hi>pag.</hi> 343. he ſets the Nobility on work, ſaying. <hi>God hath appointed the Nobility to bridle the inordinate appetite of Princes, and in ſo doing, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112413:22"/>be accuſed, as reſiſters of Authority.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Knox</hi> Appeal. fol. 33.</note> 
               <hi>It is the duty of the Nobility to repreſſe the rage and inſolencie of Princes,</hi> and then, he conjoynes the Nobility and the people together againſt the <hi>Supreme Magiſtrate,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> fol. 28. &amp; 30.</note> 
               <hi>The Nobility and Commonalty ought to reforme Religion, and in that caſe may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from honours, and may puniſh ſuch, as God hath condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> Deut. 12. <hi>of what estate, condition, or honour ſoever.</hi> For as he ſayes well in the ſame place, <hi>The puniſhment of ſuch crimes as touch the Majeſty of God, doth not appertaine to Kings and chiefe Rulers onely, but alſo to the whole body of the people, and to every member of the ſame; as occaſion, vocation, and ability ſhall ſerve to revenge the injury done againſt God.</hi> I will not ſpend time to ſhew this by your practiſes againſt <hi>Queene regent,</hi> who did oppoſe your courſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Knox</hi> hiſt. of the Church of Scot. pag. 217.</note> how by M. <hi>Knox</hi> and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, an <hi>Oath of Confederacie</hi> was taken: and <hi>the Nobility threatned to joyne with you under the paine of excommunication,</hi> pag. 272. Then an imperious letter was written to her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, that if ſhe ſhould hinder their reformation,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi> 265.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhould be compelled to take the Sword of juſt defence:</hi> and proteſted, that without the reformation which they deſired, <hi>they would never be ſubject to any mortall man.</hi> And laſt of all, They depoſed her Majeſty at the Councell of our good friend, M. <hi>Knox,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 378.</note> by a formall act penned by M. <hi>Knox,</hi> and ſet downe in his Hiſtory of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And you do well (as you ſay in your Covenant) <hi>to follow the laudable example of your Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> as dutifull children, according to that of the Wiſeman. <hi>Heare, ye children, the inſtruction of a father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>and attend to know underſtanding: for I give you good doctrine; forſake you not my law.</hi> And our worthy Father <hi>Mariana</hi> hath ſhowne you a ready way, which you, as dutifull Sonnes, have hitherto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently followed. <hi>Non diſſimulandum eſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marian. lib <hi>6.</hi> de. reg. cap. <hi>6</hi> pag. <hi>59.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>expeditam autem maxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; tutamviam eſſe, ſi publici conventus facultas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, communi conſenſu, quid ſtatuendum ſit deliberare, fixum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>túmque habere quod communi ſententià ſteterit. Monendus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primus Princept crit, atque ad ſanitatem revocandus, &amp;c. qui ſi medici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am reſpuat, neque ſpos ulla ſanitatis relinquatur, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pronunciatâ, licebit reipublica ejus imperium detractare pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m. Et qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iam bellum neceſsariò concitabitur, ejus defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112413:23"/>conſilia explicare, expedire arma, pecumias in belli ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptus imperare populis: &amp; ſi res feret, neque aliter ſe reſpub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica tueri poſſit, codem defenſionis jure, ac verò potiori au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritate &amp; propria, principem publicé hoſtem declaratum</hi> FERRO PERIMERE. This is not to bee diſſembled, that it is the moſt expedient and ſafe way, if a publike meeting may be granted, to deliberate what ſhall be done by common conſent, to hold that as firme and ſure, which ſhall be concluded by common conſent. Firſt of all, the Prince is to be admoniſhed, and to be brought to his wits againe, &amp;c. If he reject the medicine, and no hope of his recovery be left, when the ſentence is paſſed upon him, the Common-wealth may firſt refuſe his command; and becauſe of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, there will be a ſtirring up for warre, they may unfold their counſels for defence thereof, and ſhew that it is expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to have armour, and to command the people to advance moneyes for the charge of the warres. And if the matter will ſuffer, and the Common-wealth cannot otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it ſelfe, with that ſame right of defence, but with a <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter authority,</hi> and peculiar of their owne, they may kill the Prince, being declared publikely an enemy.</p>
            <p>You have followed this counſell ſo full, that you have pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed it to the laſt <hi>comma;</hi> yea, till you come to the laſt two words, FERRO PERIMERE. At which, the <hi>Anticove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanter</hi> cries out with a ſhout, <hi>God ſave the King, let his ſoule be bound up in the bundle of life.</hi> Let this dreame of <hi>Ferro per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imere</hi> be to them that hate him, and the interpretation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to his enemies.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, you ſent from <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> thouſands of letters to all corners of the kingdome for a<note n="*" place="margin">To conveene them from <hi>Dan</hi> even to <hi>Beer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>publike convention;</hi> then by the <hi>commòn conſent</hi> of all that appeare, your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (made by the chiefe men of the confederacie) was <hi>ſworn</hi> and <hi>ſubſcribed,</hi> and all of them (bound not to give obedience to the King) but to hold ſure and firme, what ſhould be thought <hi>good by common conſent.</hi> Your admonitions, ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and proteſtations have beene multiplied, but all in vaine: for, as you ſay in your proteſtations, he is ſo farre from acknowledging thoſe things to be <hi>unlawfull,</hi> which you
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112413:23"/>have condemned; that in his Proclamations he holdeth the plaine <hi>contrary opinion;</hi> and only doth remove them, as they ſay, for the hardneſſe of your heart, and to preſerve peace in the Land. And therefore, ſince he rejects your medicine, as poyſon; Is there any hope of his recoverie, that is, that ever he ſhall be of your <hi>judgements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for <hi>lata ſententia,</hi> though it be not done <hi>formally,</hi> yet it's done very <hi>materially,</hi> in every corner of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. It's a remarkable ſentence paſt by one of you, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon ſome text of the Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> (though it may be ſaid, that his Commenter was from a <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.16) <hi>The Lord hath forſaken our King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">R. B.</note> 
               <hi>and given him over to be led by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, the blinde brood of Antichriſt; who are hot begles, hunting for the blood of Gods Saints.</hi>
               <note place="margin">D.E.</note> And another preached as well, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1. Where he told, that they of the holy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant were like <hi>Iſrael at the red ſea, and Pharaoh and his Hoſt comming upon them.</hi> Another was as forward as any of them,<note place="margin">H. R.</note> When he compared the King to a wicked <hi>Italian,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to <hi>kill men both in ſoul and body.</hi> Another that he might hinder the people to ſubſcribe the Kings Covenant,<note place="margin">G.Y.</note> preached unto them, <hi>That the Kings offer of the Covenant to them was, like I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abs ſalutation of Amaſa, who tooks him by the beard, and ſaid, art thou well my brother, and then ſtabbed him in the fifth rib.</hi> And M. <hi>Cant</hi> (whom for honours ſake I name) his Sermon at <hi>Glaſgow</hi> is knowne to all our Societie, he prayed God <hi>to take away the Kings idolatry, and ſaid, that the deare Saints in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land had their noſe and their cares ſlit, for the profeſſion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.</hi> I might be infinite in this point, but becauſe it is ſo well known, I ſpare further inſtancing.</p>
            <p>The next point is <hi>Detractatio imperij,</hi> this you have done excellently, by not only refuſing obedience to his <hi>Laws civill</hi> and <hi>eccleſiaſticall,</hi> and to his <hi>Proclamations;</hi> but alſo by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall <hi>proteſting</hi> againſt him, and exhorting all to ſtand to the <hi>Covenant.</hi> You have alſo kept your <hi>counſell of war,</hi> provided <hi>Armour,</hi> laid <hi>taxations</hi> on the people to defray the charges: and the King is <hi>publicè hoſtis declaratus,</hi> publikely declared to be your enemy by the miniſterie, preſſing them to Armes by your learned informations and have taken all his Caſtles and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:112413:24"/>ſtrength from him, and ſay that they are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eyes <hi>of your owne kingdome, which you will keepe your ſelves.</hi> And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you are come ſo neere to <hi>Ferro perimere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proteſt. at <hi>Edenburg.</hi> 18. Decemb. 1938</note> that you have met him with offenſive armes. But I pray you, what made you ſtand here? what made you make a period, where was no comma? Can you think it unlawfull to kill a King, and yet ſet your muskets, pikes, and Canons before the face of a King, and ſhoot at randome? it cannot be, that you have learned <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Buchanan</hi> ſo ill, and you deſerve no reward. Let that golden ſentence of <hi>Buchanan</hi> never be forgotten. Whiles he ſaies,<note place="margin">Buch, de ſure reg. apud Scot. pag. <hi>40.</hi> Suarez. lib. <hi>6.</hi> § <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>It were good that rewards were appointed by the people, for ſuch as ſhould kill tyrants,</hi> as <hi>commonly there is for thoſe, that have killed either Wolves or Beares, or taken their whelps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your caſe was, that which is ſuppoſed by <hi>Suarez. Si ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur rex aggrediens civitatem ut illam injuſtè perdat, &amp; cives interficiat, vel quid ſimile, tunc certè licebit principi reſiſtere, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am occidendo illum, ſi aliter fieri non poſſit defenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, tum quia ſi pro vita propria hoc licet, multo magis pro communi beno, tum etiam quia civitas ipſa tunc habet juſtum bellum defenſivum, contra injuſtum invaſorem, etiamſi proprius ſit rex.</hi> If it be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned that the King is comming againſt a citie, unjuſtly to deſtroy it, and to kill the Citizens, or any ſuch like thing, Then certainly, they may reſiſt the Prince, even killing him, if they cannot otherwiſe defend themſelves: both becauſe, if this be lawfull to be done for a mans owne life, much more for the common good, and alſo becauſe the citie it ſelfe hath then a juſt defenſive warre againſt an unjuſt invader, albeit he were their owne King. This <hi>Theſis</hi> hath beene well ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died by you, for it is the ground of all your learned argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for warre.</p>
            <p>But now ſince his Majeſtie is returned backe againe with his army, and this firſt ſtorm is gone without hurt, be not you idle, but labour for ſome friends at Court who may inform you of his Majeſties <hi>Proceedings.</hi> And if you ſend any to court, let that be ever one of your inſtructions, which you gave to the Earle of <hi>Dumfermling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Novemb.</hi> 2. 1639.</note> and the Lord <hi>London. To have frequent and ſure advertiſement to you how affaires goe, with their adviſe. Amen.</hi> And he ſtill upon your guard, and let the <hi>Flac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:112413:24"/>counſell take place with you (if you heare that he ſhall refuſe to approve of your proceedings) <hi>to affright him with the terrour of inſurrection againe.</hi> And deſire all that are doubtfull and ſcrupulous of this matter to read <hi>Knox</hi> Hiſtorie and <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanans,</hi> where they ſhall finde our doctrine very cleare. The peoples power is great. <hi>Populus rege eſt praeſtantior &amp; melior, &amp;c.</hi> The people are better then the King, and of greater au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. For <hi>the people hath the ſame power over the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Buch. de jure reg. pag. <hi>61.</hi> Jdem pag. <hi>50</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that the King hath over any one perſon. Populo ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt, ut imperium cui vult deferat,</hi> the people have power to beſtow the crowne at their pleaſure? its not <hi>birthright,</hi> nor <hi>ſucceſſion,</hi> nor <hi>propinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of blood</hi> that muſt be reſpected. Therefore <hi>Knox</hi> wrote to England and Scotland; Its not <hi>birth-right only, nor propinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of blood, that maketh a King lawfully to raigne above a people, profeſſing Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>fol.</hi> 77.</note> Let his Majeſtie know that you are no <hi>Dunces,</hi> but men of learning who know the greatneſſe of your power, and the ſmalneſſe of his, notwithſtanding of the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie of Court Paraſites.</p>
            <p>But before I end this point, I cannot but admire why you have not continued your Parliament even to the end, but ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered his Majeſtie to adjourne it, you profeſſe that <hi>you follow the laudable example of your progenitors,</hi> but if you doe as they did 1560. you would not grant his Majeſtie a <hi>Negative voice,</hi> nor ſuffer the Parliament to be adjourned, but to have done with it as you did with the Aſſembly at <hi>Glaſgow, Novemb.</hi> 29. 1638. to continue it to the end, and then for the faſhion to have ſought <hi>his Approbation:</hi> for the reaſon is alike, as your aſſemblies are above him <hi>in ſpiritualibus,</hi> ſo are your Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>in temporalibus,</hi> and may bee holden though there bee neither Sword, Scepter, not Crown there. For as <hi>Knox</hi> ſaith, <hi>thoſe things were rather pompous and glorious vaine Coremonies, then any ſubſtantiall points of neceſſity required to any lawfull Parliament.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Knox</hi> hiſt. of the Church of Scotland pag. 502.</note> And therefore after you had kept that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your own accord in <hi>anno</hi> 1560. for the <hi>faſhions</hi> ſake, you ſend to the King of <hi>France,</hi> and your Scotch Queene his wife, to deſire them to ratifie the ſame. But upon their refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall you ſpake as it became you, of their ratification. <hi>We little regarded it, or yet doe regard:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem pag. <hi>500.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for all that we did was rather to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112413:25"/>ſhew our dutifull obedience, then to beg of them any ſtrength to our Religion.</hi> If you goe not thus farre, you come ſhort in following the laudable example of your Progenitors. And yet when I conſider the inſtructions given by the body of the Parliament to the Earle of <hi>Dumfermling,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Lowdon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">novemb. 2. 1639.</note> I perceive that you are not a foot behinde your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors, ſeeing you will not grant it to bee in the Kings power to prorogate the aſſembly, except, you all conſent unto it, for your ſixth Article of the <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> is thus. <hi>Item, If the King will not condeſcend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> goe on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently in Parliament, that the King prorogate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Parliament with conſent of the ſtates, according to the conditions which you have.</hi> I ſee further, that if he prorogate the aſſembly, it muſt not only be with your conſent, but alſo hee muſt grant your petition ſent to his Majeſtie, by the Earle of <hi>Kinoull</hi> from the Parliament; before you will grant to any peaceable concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or prorogation of the Parliament: for your ſole Argument to have your petition granted in is theſe words. <hi>Without this point be granted, it is not poſſible to make a peaceable concluſion, or that they can reſt ſatisfied with the prorogation of the Parliament.</hi> And leſt that the people ſhould reſt ſatisfied herewith, and your <hi>Democracie</hi> take no good ſucceſſe, the Miniſters would be exhorted to doe their part, not to ſuffer the people to ſettle upon their dregs, but to hold them in perpetuall motion till it end, to your perpetuall quietneſſe. This was the practiſe of the zealous Miniſters your Predeceſſors in the dayes of Queene-<hi>Regent,</hi> Queene <hi>Many,</hi> and in the tender age of King <hi>Iames,</hi> who did both in private and publike oppone them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to authoritie for the maintenance of our tenents con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>civill Magiſtrate,</hi> and our other Prerogatives. This made King <hi>Iames</hi> our common enemie, ſpeake the truth in exceeding harſh termes, while he ſaid. <hi>E miniſterio homines nonnulli praecipites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſilic. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron. pag. <hi>147.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ignei, audaces, in hac humanarum divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rúm<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> rerum confuſione, tam gratioſi apud plebem facti ſunt, ut deguſtata dominationis dulcedine, ceperunt Democraticam reipub. formam ſibi ſomniare; &amp; primo aviae, deinede matris meae ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione elati (&amp; nimirum blandiebatur ijs ſucceſſus) poſtrem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lari mea aetate ad Democratiae ſua ſtabilimentum diu abuſi, jam
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112413:25"/>poteſtatem tribunitiam ſpecerta deveraverant: ut in populari re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publica cunt plebem, quò vellent facilè circumducerent, omnium negotiorum momenta ſoli temperarent. Ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nulla in mea pupil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lari atate vel poſt, ſeditie contigit, quin hos homines ſui furoris &amp; amentiae patronos ſeditioſi facere conati ſuut. Crebra adverſus me in tribunitijs concionibus calumnta ſpargchantur, non quod crimen aliquod deſignaſſem, ſed quia rex cram, quod omni crimine pejus habebatur.</hi> Some head-ſtrong, fierie, bold men of the Miniſters in this confuſion of humane and divine things, became ſo gracious with the multitude, that having taſted the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of government, they beganne to dreame to themſelves a Democraticall forme of the Common-wealth. And firſt being puffed up with the overthrow of my Grand-mother: and ſecondly, of my owne mother, (and truly their ſucceſſe ſlattered them:) Laſt of all, having long time abuſed my ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der age for the eſtabliſhing of their Democracie, they had already by an aſſured hope fully taken to themſelves a tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiall power: that in a popular Common-wealth, they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ruled all buſineſſe of moment, ſeeing they might eaſily leade the people, whither they pleaſed. And therefore, no ſedition hath hapned either in my tender age or afterward, wherein the ſeditious did not make thoſe men (the Miniſters) the patrons of their furie and madneſſe. There were frequent calumnies ſcattered abroad in their Tribunitiall ſermons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, not that I had committed any crime, but becauſe I was a King, which was eſteemed worſe than al crims. Indeed I finde our Father <hi>Becanus</hi> telling the ſame, that you are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Monarchie, in the example of Queen <hi>Mary. An non Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reniſſima Maria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Recan examen. Concord. Angl.</note> 
               <hi>Sereniſſimi Jacobi mater habuit primatum temporalem in Scotia? omnino habuit, An non per vos de facto privata eſt? Nemo dubitat.</hi> Had not the moſt illuſtrious Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> the mother of the moſt excellent King <hi>Iames,</hi> the Supremacie <hi>in temporall things</hi> in Scotland? [for neither you nor we will let them have it in <hi>ſpirituall things</hi>] certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe had it: but did not you deprive her of it? no man doubts of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XI"/> I will follow out then another paralell, and that in, <hi>De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acâ obedientiâ.</hi> Of blind obedience, which we both requice
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112413:26"/>now of our people. Your Covenant was mightily called in queſtion, even by the Commons, and yet you forced them to ſweare, and ſubſcribe it upon your bare word? telling them, that ſince the Church men have ſworn and ſubſcribed it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that the Commons ought to do it, <hi>and follow their Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, whom God at this time hath largely furniſhed with courage and counſell, for the good of his Kirk and Kingdome.</hi> I heare, that the things which you have condemned in your generall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, where in the judgement of the common people of a contrary nature; but now, having in their Covenant ſworn in <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>practiſe,</hi> to follow the determination of the firſt generall aſſemblie that ſhould be kept, they are forced to forſake their owne judgement, and embrace the contrary, by vertue of the power of the generall aſſemblie. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we ſay: The people are to ſubject to their Leaders, that if they erre in defining any doubt, the people<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>vi regiminis,</hi> by the force of our government over them, ought to erre. For in this blinde obedience, * <hi>requiritur proprij voluntatis &amp; judicij abu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatio, mancipatio &amp; in poteſtatem ſuperioris deditio.</hi> There is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the deny all of our owne will and judgement, and a giving our ſelves over, as ſlaves in the power of our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. To this purpoſe your <hi>Andrew Cant</hi> (whom I name oft for honours ſake) anſwered as he was very able to doe, to thoſe who would have heard of him ſome reaſons for the ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Covenant, which he ſo earneſtly recommended in <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> and never brought a reaſon for it; he told them true, that they muſt <hi>deny learning and reaſon, and helpe Chriſt a lift.</hi> And our ever honoured Generall, the firſt founder of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, <hi>Jguatius Loyola,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ignat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſt. de viatut. obed. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> tels us that <hi>Prudentia eſt imperantis non obedientis.</hi> Wiſdome belongeth to the Commander, not to the obeyer. And therefore his ordinance is this to his followers. <hi>Statuere debetis vobiſcum quicquid ſuperior pracipit ipſius Dei praceptum eſſe &amp; voluntatem, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ut ad credenda que fides ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic a proponit, tot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> animo aſſenſu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> veſtro ſtatim incumbit is, ſic adea facienda quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuperior dixerit, caco quoda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> impetu voluntatis parenda cupida, ſine ullâ prorſû diſquiſitione feramini.</hi> You ought to reſolve with your ſelves that whatſoever your Superiour commands you, is the command and will of God
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112413:26"/>himſelf. And even as you without delay yeeld with full mind and aſſent to believe thoſe things which the Catholike faith propones, ſo you ought to be carried to the doing of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your ſuperiour ſhal ſay, with a certain blind force of a wil, that is deſirous to obey. So ſaid your <hi>Cant</hi> in that ſame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> while he told the people, to whom he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the Covenant, <hi>That he was ſent to them with a commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from Chriſt to bid them ſubſcribe the Covenant, which was Chriſts contract, and that he himſelf was come as a wooer to them for the bridegroom, and called upon them to come to be hand-faſted by ſubſcribing that contract.</hi> And told them plainly, <hi>that he would not depart the town, till he got the names of all, who ſhould refuſe to ſubſcribe that contract, of whom he promiſed to complain to his Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XII"/> I have yet more matter of congratulation: for, wheras for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly you did hold that Eccleſiaſtical laws do not <hi>bind the conſcience,</hi> you do well now to maintain the contrary. And therfore you have deſervedly depoſed, &amp; thruſt from amongſt you, thoſe miniſters, who only offered to ſuffer your laws bind the <hi>outward man,</hi> and to conforme with you in <hi>practiſe,</hi> but would not covenant with you, nor ſweare to be of your <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> As for example. They promiſed to <hi>ſit</hi> at the receiving of the Communion, as you do ſit on your tail, and thus would conform in <hi>practiſe</hi> with you, but they requeſted you not to burden their <hi>conſcience,</hi> to believ <hi>ſitting only neceſſary,</hi> and that <hi>keeling</hi> is <hi>Idolatry.</hi> The like may be inſtane'd in al the reſt of the matters controverted amongſt you. Since they would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conform in <hi>practiſe,</hi> and only differ in <hi>judgement;</hi> why might not you compell them to ſubſcribe the covenant, and make them ſwear with you <hi>before God and the world, that they were convinc'd in their conſciences, of the lawfulnes of ſuch things?</hi> The Scripture bids <hi>compel men to the wedding,</hi> neither need you regard them, who call your <hi>holy violence</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh inquiſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XIII"/> Furthermore, I am confident that you ſhall not bee ſuch enemies to our <hi>workes of Supererogation,</hi> as formerly you have beene: For when the King urged you to ſubſcribe the <hi>confeſſion of Faith,</hi> you refuſed it, drawing your reaſon from the very ground, which hath produced all our <hi>workes of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:112413:27"/>which is this, <hi>That a good worke, which is done of a mans owne accord, is more excellent then that which is done by command of a Superiour,</hi> as you reaſon learnedly in your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation in <hi>September</hi> 1638. and ſo conclude, that you have done a more ſyncere worke, and acceptable in covenanting without authoritie, than if you ſhould do it now at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of your Superiour: for, (as you ſay) thus doing, <hi>the more libertie, the leſſe hypocriſie, and more ſynceritie hath appeared.</hi> If this ground of yours be removed, then both your <hi>Covenant,</hi> and our <hi>Evangelicall Councels</hi> will periſh. And yet the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covenanter</hi> will ſay, that the Scripture cals him the <hi>good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> that doth his <hi>Maſters will:</hi> and whoſoever do more than they are commanded by their Maſters, get <hi>Affricanus</hi> thanks: <hi>Non amo nimium diligentes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XIIII"/> I thought to have congratulated with you, that you are moſt like unto us in <hi>Equivocation;</hi> for your own ends, to perſwade the people to believ, that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> your own heart knoweth to be moſt falſe. As for example, to perſwade the people before they did ſubſcribe the covenant, that it is for defence of the King, againſt whom (you ſay) no man is bound by the covenant to riſe up in deſenſive arms: and that you are only bound to <hi>ſuffer,</hi> if his Majeſty were to invade you. But when they have ſubſcribed, then you tell them that they muſt provide armour, to <hi>reſiſt</hi> the Kings comming to <hi>invade you.</hi> This made many poor ſimple men complain, that they were wronged, and that they would at leaſt be <hi>perjured,</hi> if they ſhould do ſo. Yet the Scripture is plain for ſuch equivocation: for when the army ſent by the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> came to <hi>Dothan,</hi> where the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> was to fetch him to the King, the Prophet came out to them,<note place="margin">2 King 6.19.</note> and ſaid, <hi>This is not the way, neither is this the city, follow me, and I will bring you to the man whom you ſeek. But he led them to Samaria,</hi> the quite contrary way. But here is the difference between you and the Prophet, that when he had miſled them and brought them to Samaria, he did not detain them as cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives from their Maſters, but ſaid, <hi>Set bread and water before them, that they may eat and drinke, and goe to their Maſters.</hi> But you doe not ſo, but keepe them in the net, in the which they are taken, that they cannot eſcape; but muſt joyne with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112413:27"/>you againſt their Maſter: to whom they ſhall not returne, but with defenſive armes; ſuch as are not ſhield and buckler, but pike, musket, and canon. I commend your policie herein, for you know, that the King doth not thinke, that the common people did ever aime at the <hi>contents</hi> and <hi>conſequents</hi> of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and ſo doth not impute any <hi>diſloyalty</hi> unto them: and when he ſees that you have them ſo cloſe tied unto you, they become your <hi>buckler</hi> and <hi>defenſive armes;</hi> for whoſe ſake he hath ſpared you, whom he thinks to be heads of <hi>a faction</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, ſo that here <hi>multitudo ſociorum parit impunitatem criminum.</hi> And to ſpeak the truth, ſeeing he condemnoth your <hi>zeal to religion,</hi> as if <hi>it were rehellion</hi> againſt him; and yet hath given you ſuch way, without curbing your courſe in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, we cannot but ſay, that his innate Love to his anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Kingdome, wherof he hath given plentifull teſtimonies, hath brought him to this ſtrait, that he hath neglected his Fathers direction, which he was taught by <hi>exper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce,</hi> and which King <hi>Charles</hi> will teach his Son by a <hi>double example.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Doron pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> The direction was this, <hi>Si ab initio clementians oſtentes, creſcet in immenſum delinquentium numerus, creſcet tui contemptus: &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>àm punire volueris, major erit ſontium quàm inſontium numerus, nec promptum erit diſcern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re unde facere oporteat initium panae. At que it a multos perdes invitus, quos tempeſtivâ pancorum poenâ ſervare potuiſſes. Tu meo ex exemplo potes hic eſſe cautior, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go cum manſuetudine mea inſtituiſſem populum trahere ad legum obedientians; contrà accidit ut omnia plena facta ſint tumultibus. Ego verò promercede né grates quidem retule im.</hi> If at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning thou ſhew clemencie, the number of delinquents will greatly increaſe, and the contempt of thy ſelfe will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: and when thou wilt puniſh delinquents, the number of the guilty will be more than of the innocent, neither ſhall it be ready for thee to diſcern, whereat thou muſt begin pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. And ſo thou ſhalt deſtroy many againſt thy will, which thou mighteſt ſave by the timely puniſhment of a few. In this point thou maiſt be more warie by my example: For when I had purpoſed by meekneſſe, to draw the people to the obedience of the laws, the contrary happened; ſo that all was filled with uproares, And as for me, I got not ſo much as thanks for my reward.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:112413:28"/>
But go you on, and that you may more and more perſwade them to adhere unto you, tell them, as you doe, that if they ſhall come under the Kings power, he will utterly deſtroy them; and that his Proclamations and promiſes are not to be regarded, ſince in your judgement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hath broken the oath at his Coronation, when he ſware to God to defend his truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but would now, if you did not re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt him, deſtroy the religion, the laws and liberties of this Church and Kingdome, as your Proteſtations and Informations for warre do fully ſhew.</p>
            <p>It was alſo a notable Equivocation, whereby you thruſt the ſimple people from ſubſcribing the Kings Covenant, commanded by his Majeſty to be ſubſcribed, as it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in <hi>anno</hi> 1581. and not according to your new interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation added unto it. For in the 1581. it was a Covenant drawne up at his Majeſties ſpeciall Command, and by his <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall authority,</hi> the oath and ſubſcription was preſcribed to his Subjects, and ſo they ſware according to the meaning of the King, that was the exacter of this Oath. So that while his Majeſty requireth it now to be ſubſcribed, as it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed then, he doth it in oppoſition to this preſent time, wherein you have put a new Commenter upon it, directly contrary to the meaning of King <hi>Iames,</hi> who firſt preſcribed it. And it's too evident that Ieſuitiſme and Puritaniſme were both odious to him, and that it was his chiefe labour (as he ſayes himſelfe) to hold up that which you are caſting down, ſo that one of you doth not erre, while you call him your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie <hi>in ſuperlativo, infeſtiſſimus hoſtis.</hi> But you did hinder this ſubſcription by a moſt excellent Equivocation, while you ſay. <hi>That you would be guilty of mocking of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proteſt. Sept. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>and take his name in vain: and as we are not to multiply miracles on Gods part; ſo ought we not to multiply oathes and covenants on our part, and thus to play with oaths, as children do with toyes.</hi> Thus the people who were with-holden from the Covenant, thinke that all was true, which you ſaid, not obſerving that it was an Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and alſo a <hi>pia fraus:</hi> for if they had but obſerved your practice, they would have ſeen it contrary to this reaſon of yours; for how oft have you ſworne and ſubſcribed your own covenant? At <hi>Edinburgh</hi> where you made it, it was ſworne
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:112413:28"/>and ſubſcribed by you; when you came home to your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, it was reiterated ſolemnly by you; when you went to other Pariſhes, you did, as good examples to them, renew it againe and againe; and thought it no <hi>mocking of God, nor mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying of oaths, or taking his name in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſwer to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hamiltions</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</note>But I obſerve another notable Equivocation, which is ſo profound in one part of it, that I think we muſt be your diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to learne it: while you ſay, <hi>The ſwearer is not bound to the meaning of the preſcriber of the Oath, nor to his owne mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but is obliged to the reality</hi> rei juratae. I am ſorry that you were put to this ſtrait, to finde out this evaſion. The truth was (as I perceive) that your affrighting them <hi>with mocking of God, and taking his name in vaine,</hi> did not hinder, but many thouſands did ſubſcribe after the <hi>Lord Commiſſioner,</hi> and Lords of Counſell. And this oath being taken, as it was in the 1581. yeare of God, when King <hi>James</hi> exacted it, it is too evident a conſequence, that all that have taken this oath, are ſo farre from abjuring Epiſcopacie and the Articles of Perth, &amp;c. that by the contrary, they are obliged to defend the ſame: So that they may ſay with King <hi>James,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proteſt. Sept. 1638.</note> 
               <hi>Mihi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipuus labor eſt dejectos epiſcopos reſtituere, &amp; Puritanorum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchian expuguare.</hi> Now, though in your proteſtation againſt the ſubſcription of it, you made it one of your reaſons why you could not ſubſcribe it, becauſe it was to be exacted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaning of the exacter, which is King <hi>Charles,</hi> Heire of his Fathers opinions, as well as of his Dominions: yet ſince it is ſubſcribed by many, according to the meaning of the exacter, you remove that rub, by ſaying, that they are not bound to ſweare and ſubſcribe according to the meaning of the preſcriber of the oath. This is well, for then, when any taketh an oath, he may ſweare, not according to the exacters meaning, but according to his owne; and ſo none needs to know what we ſweare.</p>
            <p>But the ſubſcribers will ſay, we took the oath according to the meaning of the <hi>preſcriber,</hi> and both our meanings, both who did <hi>exact</hi> and <hi>take</hi> the oath, was, that Epiſcopacie and Perths articles vvere not abjured. To this you anſvver, that they are not bound to take it according to either of their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112413:29"/>but according to the realitie <hi>rei juratae.</hi> If it be ſo, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the exacter, nor the taker of the oath did know what they ſware and ſubſcribed unto. If this be to ſweare blinde obedience, I approve it, if not, I will be glad to be farther made perfect in equivocating: for I can finde no third, but either the oath muſt be taken according to the meaning of the <hi>exacter,</hi> or of the <hi>taker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I take your meaning to be, that that oath of the <hi>Kings Covenant</hi> ought to be taken, as we thought to have done with the <hi>Oath of allegiance</hi> taken by Romane Catholikes in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. The King with his Councell uſed all the wit and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that could be had, to cauſe them to take the oath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>Equivocation,</hi> or <hi>mentall reſervation,</hi> and that they ſhould take no <hi>diſpenſation</hi> from the Pope, for taking ſuch an oath: ſo that in this caſe, it was made ſo cleare, that both the <hi>preſcriber</hi> and the <hi>taker</hi> of the oath could not differ, but be of one mind. But our <hi>Paſcenius</hi> did laugh this diligence to ſcorne, and found out a prettie way to elude ſuch an oath, by telling them, that if the Pope did diſſolve that oath, and declare it unlawfull, they were no more tied to ſuch an oath.<note place="margin">Paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. Reſpon. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. i Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tor. Iacob. Reg. tit. <hi>B. 2.3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vide (inquit) in tanta aſtutia quanta fit ſimplicitas, juramentum tot circumstantiis connexuiſſe exiſtimabat, ut ſalvâ conſcientiâ, nullâ ratione à quoquam diſſolvi poſſit. Sed videre non potuit, fi pontifex juramentum diſſolverit, omnes illius nexus, ſive de fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Regi praeſtanda, ſive de diſpenſatione non admittenda, pariter diſſolutos fore. Immo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliud dicam admirabilius, juramentum fi injuſtum aperte declaretur, neminem obligat, ſed</hi> ipſo facto <hi>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſt. Regis verò juramentum injuſtum eſſe abi ipſo eccleſiae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore ſufficienter declaratum eſt. Vides jam in fumum abiiſse illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us obligationem, ut vinculum quod a tot ſapientibus f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rreum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabatur, minus ſit quàm ſtramineum.</hi> Behold (ſayes he) how much ſimplicity is in ſo much ſubtilty; he thought to have bound this oath by ſo many circumſtances, that it could be diſſolved no manner of way by any man with a ſafe conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. But he could not ſee, that, if the Pope ſhould diſſolve this oath, all the knots of it, whether it be of fidelity to be performed to the King, or of a diſpenſation not to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are both alike diſſolved. Yea, I will tell another more
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:112413:29"/>marvellous thing, if it be openly declared that the oath is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, it doth oblige no man, but by the fact it ſelfe it is null. Now this oath of the King is ſufficiently declared by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of the Church himſelfe to be unjuſt. Now thou ſees that the obligation of it is evaniſhed in ſmoake: ſo that, that bond, which by ſo many wiſemen was thought to be ſtrong as iron, is weaker than a rope of ſtraw.</p>
            <p>Thus it was with your Covenant; King <hi>Charles</hi> was very carefull to have it ſubſcribed according to his Fathers mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who did preſcribe the oath <hi>anno</hi> 1581. and his owne meaning, which was the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me with his Fathers, who appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> and <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rths Articles.</hi> So that all equivocation is here excluded: But (this <hi>Paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enius</hi> trick makes all cleare) if <hi>Dickson</hi> or <hi>Henderſon,</hi> &amp;c. ſhall diſſolve this oath, and declare it unlawfull, it hath no force, as being not according to the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality</hi> of the things themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves: and thus, are none more tied to the King by Covenant, but may break it as eaſily as <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> did his cords, and muſt run your courſe againſt his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. I might inſiſt on many inſtances to prove Equivocation amongſt you, if it were needfull, but I am conſident you ſhall not be ſuch enemies to it in time to come.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XV"/> Moreover, your <hi>pie fraudes</hi> have not a little advanced your courſes, for though the generall cauſe of all this uproare was pretended to be for defence of religion, lawes and liberties, yet (to ſpeake under the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe) it flowed from private cauſes and reſpects, for (not to ſpeak of the contempt of Monarchy, nor of private frettin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt Soveraignty by malecontents) the courſe his Majeſty was taking with the tythes, to deliver the miniſtry, and meaner ſort of the Laitie from that which was counted bondage and ſlaverie, made many fret to ſee themſelves robbed of that clientely and dependance of the Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rgie and Laitie, and of that power, command and ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, which by the tye of tythes they did enjoy. Some had their private quarrels againſt the Biſhops, many could not abide to ſee them preferred to be on his Majeſties ounſell, &amp;c. And a great hatred was working againſt them, for being the chiefe inſtruments that the Miniſters maintenance was augmented, and many of the Tythes reſtored backe againe,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:112413:30"/>which made many thinke that in the end all the tythes, and Church-lands would returne to the ancient owner, whereby many would be brought to a poore eſtate, if the tythes were taken from them, and ſome who have made Churches their habitation, would not have a dwelling place at all; and ſome others being ambitious of preferment both in Church and Policie, were no ſmall cauſes of all this uproare. Now how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, from thoſe and ſuch like other motives, this diſorder hath come: yet its well diſſembled by you, in taking this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, to work your private intended ends, by making the multitude believe that all is for defence of Religion, Lawes and liberties, which otherwiſe would be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>His Holineſſe our Pope, did never laugh more heartily, than when it was told him, that you made the people believe that the book of Common Prayer was penned at Rome, and ſent to the King, and that it was nothing but the maſſe turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Engliſh; and that the King was a Papiſt, and intended to change the Religion. That your Biſhops were Penſioners to the Pope, and that all, who would not ſubſcribe your cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, are Papiſts; truly he commended your Policie, to catch children with wiles, and men with lies. The aſperſions you have caſt upon King, Biſhops, and Anticovenanters will make you noble. It's a good policie ſtill to complaine of Court and State, and to prie into great mens lives, to picke out ſome fault, and to make faults where we finde none: ſtill with <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſaying, The men who have good and right cauſes,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.3.4.</note> have no man to heare them, <hi>Oh that I were made Iudge in the land, that every man which hath any ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it or cauſe, might come unto me, and I would do him juſtice.</hi> Thus the ſilly multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude will lightly apprehend that you are blameleſſe, who doe ſo narrowly trie and crie out againſt the faults of others, whom howbeit you do not wound, yet in the vulgar opinion you do greatly ſtaine and blot them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XVI"/> Finally, we have both ſuffered much of our enemies for our <hi>practiſe againſt Kings and Princes,</hi> in cutting them away that are enemies to the religion. We need not be aſhamed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that the <hi>armour</hi> wherwith ſuch kings are killed, are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in <hi>our ſhop:</hi> you know that <hi>Hackes</hi> and <hi>Coppinger</hi> who
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:112413:30"/>wrote to Scotland to <hi>Iames Gibſon,</hi> that he with the adviſe of the brethren, might tell their opinion concerning the ſpirit that moved them, &amp; the act that they had in hand to be done, for the delivery of <hi>T. Cart wright</hi> out of priſon, and killing of all their withſtanders. That which <hi>Ravillack</hi> did <hi>effectu,</hi> was no more praiſe-worthy than that which they did <hi>affectu:</hi> all thoſe our works are not to be accounted points of <hi>treaſon,</hi> but onely <hi>ſenſible expreſſions</hi> of our Heroicall Zeale to the <hi>defence of Religion,</hi> which ought to be more deare to us, than Kings or Princes, father or mother, brother or ſiſter, all thoſe cords muſt be broke, and bonds caſt from us, when we ſee them to ſet themſelves to take counſell againſt the Lords Annointed. Such men of courage who put their life in their hand, and cut off ſuch wicked men, ought to be ſo farre from being counted traitors, that they ſhould be rewarded for doing it, as your <hi>Buchanan</hi> ſayes. <hi>Knox</hi> in his hiſtory of Scotland commends the privie murdering of the Cardinall of S. <hi>Andrewes</hi> perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated by Norman <hi>Leſley</hi> ſonne to the Earle of <hi>Rothſey,</hi> and <hi>Iames Melvin</hi> cals it a godly fact, and propones it as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to be followed by the poſterity.</p>
            <p>In your Zions plea, and other papers, you ſpeak excellently of that Heroicall fact of <hi>Felton</hi> your Martyr,<note place="margin">Du. Buck.</note> and pathetically exhort the Nobles of the Land to follow his footſteps, ſaying, <hi>God hath chalked out the way unto you, God having offered himſelf to guide you by the hand, in giving this first blow, will you not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low home? the ſprinkling of the blood of the wolf, if we can f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llow the Lord in it, may prove a meanes to ſave us. The counſell of Huſhai to Abſalom forteth well with this buſineſſe, that all Iſrael ſhould be gathered from Dan to Beerſheba, as the ſand on the ſea in number, who may with the ropes of their Prayers joyned</hi> to the power of your hands, <hi>draw the city of their Babel into the river of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, untill there be not one ſmall ſtone found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have moſt zealouſly embraced this profitable exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and albeit your intended work tooke but ſmall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, yet let not this interruption bequench your zeale, nor cauſe your heroicall ſpirits to ſaile, but be forward in this cauſe, and let all your words be ſpoken by Talents, that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority may ſee that you do not ſcare it. Let our example
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:112413:31"/>encourage you; and your example encourage us. It was to this purpoſe manfully ſaid by one of you.<note place="margin">Payne epiſt. to F.</note> 
               <hi>Our zeale to Gods glory, our love to his Church, and the due planting of the ſame, in this horeheaded age ſhould be ſo warm, and ſtirring in us, as not to care what adventure we gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and what cenſure Wee abide,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Ieſuites and Seminaries their diabolicall bolaneſſe (he wrongs us in his epithet, ſeing he followe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our way) will cover our faces with ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Its true indeed, ſo long as we are not able to reſiſt, and make out party good by ſtrength of hand, there is a neceſſity that we muſt ſuffer, and like the poore man <hi>we muſt uſe entreaty:</hi> for its our wiſdome to conſider the times, when we may be forward, and when not. Hence it was that in the dayes of Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> when your power was little, that your anſwer was humble; for when the State and Clergie of England charged your ſort of men with <hi>faction, ſedition</hi> and <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> and iudged that if you were curbed betimes, you would bring <hi>deſolation</hi> on Church &amp; policie: your anſwer was mild (though it might ſeeme to your adverſaries mixt with paſſion, pride and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie) while you ſaid.<note place="margin">Practiſe of Prelates.</note> 
               <hi>Peace was by thoſe men kept inviolate, for which of them ever dealt diſorderly, or tumultuouſly? who ever of them in word or deed gave out any juſt ſuſpicion of unpeaceable dealing? nay have they not in their miniſtery, in their examples, ſtriven for peace more then any?</hi> for this cauſe (as your <hi>Buch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> wel obſerveth with us) <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Romans ſayes. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to ſuperior powers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Buch de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure reg. pag <hi>5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Ibid. pag. <hi>56.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> (ſaies hee) <hi>writes this in the infancy of the Church, there were but few Chriſtians then, not many of th m rich, or of ability, ſo as they were not ripe for ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſe, as if a man ſh uld write to ſuch Chriſtians as are und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the Lurke, in ſubſtance poore in courage feeble, in ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ength unarmed, in number few, and generally ſubject to al kina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of injuries: would he not write as Paul did? So as the Apoſtle did reſpect the men h wrote unto, and his words are not to be extended to the body, or people of a Common-wealth, or whole city</hi> And he tels us in this caſe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bid. pag. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> if <hi>Paul</hi> were alive and did ſee wicked Kings raigning in Chriſtian Common-wealths, <hi>Paul</hi> would ſay, <hi>That he accounted no ſuch for Magiſtrates he would forbid all men for ſpeaking unto them, and from keeping
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:112413:31"/>them Company: he would leave them to their ſubjects to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rel. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Pont. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>neither would he blame them, if they accounted no ſuch longer for their Kings.</hi> And as <hi>Bellarm.</hi> ſayes, <hi>Talis conſenſu omnium po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, into debet privari ſuo dominio. Si hoc priſcis temporibus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus factum ſit, cauſa eſt, quia deerant vires.</hi> Such a King by the conſent of all may, yea ought to be deprived of his dominion: if this in old times was not done, the cauſe was, becauſe they had no ſtrength.</p>
            <p>But now the times are changed, <hi>Hac atas alios mores poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat,</hi> this age requireth other manners, ſpare not big words, <hi>tell the head its ſick, preſſe the people to armes too, ſtrike the Baſiliske veine, ſince nothing but that will cure the pluriſie of your eſtate.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenanters informe for Defenſive. 5.2.</note> Your ſtrength is great, yea ſo great that you profeſſe your ſelves invincible, <hi>if you k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epe unitie and veritie,</hi> that is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which I congratulate.</p>
            <p>Certainly, you have an invincible Generall, your <hi>head Leſley.</hi> And as there is great union between us in doctrine and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; ſo I perceive a great ſimilitude between both our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, our <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> and your <hi>Leſley.</hi> As for their birth, I cannot compare them, for neither <hi>Maphaeus,</hi> nor <hi>Ribadeneira,</hi> nor <hi>Valderana,</hi> nor <hi>Becanus,</hi> nor any that writes his life, tels us, who were his parents; ſo that it ſeems <hi>pater Ignatii fuit du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bii generis, &amp; mater communis generis.</hi> As for his life,<note place="margin">Maphaeus in Vu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. lib. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> we deny not the truth, for as our own writers ſay of his <hi>childhood. ſatis conſtat cum in pueritià, profanos admodum hauſiſſe ſpiritus.</hi> It is certain, that in his childhood he drew in very prophane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. And in <hi>adoleſcentià, militiae ac vanitati ſeſe dedit.</hi> In his childhood, he gave himſelf to wars and vanity,<note place="margin">Ribad. de vit Ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> being ready to ſerve any man for his pay, ſo that our <hi>Ribadencira</hi> caleth him <hi>Vanitatis vile mancipium,</hi> A vile ſlave of vanity.</p>
            <p>But at <hi>Pompeiopolis</hi> being couragiouſly fighting, his leg was ſore wounded, and it was good for him,<note place="margin">Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in.</note> for <hi>ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epto hoc luculento vulnere, ad Deum converſus eſt.</hi> Having gotten this great wound, he was converted to God, and his leg was amended; but yet, <hi>non nihil claudicavit, ſeà honeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ribad. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; quod ambulan li moderatione tegeretur:</hi> He halted a little, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently, and which he might hide by the moderation of his walking, and become the founder and generall of our holy
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:112413:32"/>
               <hi>Society.</hi> All this hath hapned to your Generall, in his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, youth-hood, in his wound, in his halting, in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and becomming Generall of your holy Society. But from the halting of both our Generals, the <hi>Anticovenanters</hi> draw an ominous concluſion, that wee are like Iſrael in the daies of <hi>Elias, halting betweene God and Baal, and running cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked courſes.</hi> But notwithſtanding of our halting, they ſhall find that we can run, and give them matter enough to worke on. They have ſo ſenſibly found it ſo, in our Generall <hi>Ignatius,</hi> that all in our Church, who are not of our order, wiſh that he had never beene hurt in warre, that ſo he might have there remained, and never turned home, where in peace he doth more hurt, then he did in warres; for abroad (ſay they) hee fought againſt the common enemy, but at home, he raiſeth and foſtereth ſeditions and treaſons againſt Princes. The ſame do many of you ſay of <hi>Leſley,</hi> and apply that to him, which our men ſpeake of our <hi>Loyola.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Quam bello plus pace noces, &amp; ad otia verſus</l>
               <l>Crudelis animum vertis ad inſidias.</l>
               <l>Scotia &amp; in media conſcripto milite regnas,</l>
               <l>Dira<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> (fraterno nomine) bella geris.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But I pray you, as we have followed our Generall <hi>Ignatius</hi> his command, by yeelding up our ſelves, our wils and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>cacâ obedientiá,</hi> as he did require; ſo do you with your Generall, in following his command and directions. And ſo much rather I require this of you, becauſe I heare, there are <hi>diviſions among you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.18.</note> 
               <hi>and partly I believe it, for there muſt be alſo hereſies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt.</hi> But you may amend this breach, conſider wiſely, where the diviſion is likelieſt to bee, and prepare your ſalve for every mans ſore, and your bait for every mans humour. If it be among the Nobilitie, then extoll and praiſe what they have done, tell, that all mens eyes are upon them, as the noble reformers of the Land; let them heare of the noble facts of their progenitors, commend perſeverance, and ſhew them what cowatdize is, and what infamie will follow to yeeld to their Prince. Put them in remembrance of that noble ſentence of ours.<note place="margin">To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>6</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si nobilis invaſus, poſſet vitam ſervare fugie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>do, non
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:112413:32"/>tenetur (ſi inde infamiam contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t) fugere, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d hoſtem occider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> potest.</hi> If a noble man being invaded, may ſave his life by fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet he is not bound to fly, if he contract infamie thereby, he is rather bound to kill his enemy, much leſſe to yeeld. Let the women in the ſtreets continue to preſerre thoſe young <hi>Davids</hi> ten times above their Prince, and ſtill pray for them. And if there be any of the Nobilitie of greater worth, tell them, that the whole buſineſſe depends upon them, and that you will doe all by their direction, and that they ſhall bee made immortal, by recording their acts to poſterity to come.</p>
            <p>If you ſeare diviſion in the miniſtery, it's eaſie to help that, keepe thoſe under, who are not zealous in your cauſe: let them not be acquainted with your myſteries, nor be choſen Commiſſioners for aſſemblies: if there be any matter of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to be commended to the people ſend either conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly or ſeverally, ſome zealous miniſters to their pulpits, to rouze up the multitude, and put the like edge upon ſuch cold-riſe miniſters, and if they become not more zealous, put them in feare of <hi>Deprivation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you feare any diviſion among the Commons, it's likely that ſome of them have ſeene the Kings extraordinary ſavour toward them: but you ought to be carefull, that they ſee not the Kings Proclamations; and if any have ſeen them, let them be perſwaded that his Majeſties Proclamations have this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly end, to divide them, and then to deſtroy them; and that all other faire promiſes ſhall have no reall performances. Be not you behind the King in your promiſes to them alſo, and howbeit, you have a hundred thouſand pound to take of them, yet be not ſuddaine, but by delaying; put them in hope that you will never exact it: For if you goe now to exact it, it will make them repine and grumble, and ſay, inſtead of <hi>Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mons</hi> eaſie yoke, we are oppreſſed with <hi>Rehoboams</hi> heavie burdens, and ſo make a rupture, and returne every man to his tent, and in the end ſubmit themſelves to their <hi>Salomon</hi> againe. And eſpecially, let the ruling Elders command their ruled Elders, or miniſters, to be diligent in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, to keepe the multitude in their zealous humour, for if they doe not unceſſantly blow upon them, they will be like
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:112413:33"/>
               <hi>mare mortuum,</hi> and never be moved. Ceaſe not to poſſeſſe them with an evill opinion, of all that oppones themſelves to your courſes either by word or writing, make them believe that all, that writ againſt your confederacie, are unnaturall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to their Countrie, and that it is not againſt your faction which they doe, but againſt Church and Kingdome; and ſuffer no man to deny this to be a Nationall quarrell, or to call it a Faction, and all that refuſe to caſt in their lot with you, call them the curſed inhabitants of <hi>Meroz,</hi> that will not help you againſt the mightie.</p>
            <p>And let all that follow their King, be called the <hi>Kings fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> according to the example of your progenitors, who cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all that followed the Queen, <hi>a faction,</hi> which they would puniſh, as <hi>Traitors; whenſoever God ſhould put the ſword of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in their hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Knox.</hi> hiſt. of the Church of Scotland. pag. 364.</note> that is, when they ſhould find themſelves able to depoſe the Queen, (as they did) and repreſſe her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. There is another thing which I deſire you to remember to try where thoſe miniſters, that have beene moſt oppoſite to our doctrines and practiſes, have had their reſidence in the miniſterie, that you may place able and zealous men for our cauſe in thoſe ſame places, to build up the people which they have deſtroyed. This worke is well begun by you, in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Henderſon</hi> from the Countrie, to the town of <hi>Edinburgh, Dikson</hi> to <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> and <hi>Rhetorfort</hi> and <hi>Blair</hi> (who could not get libertie to vent our Doctrine elſewhere) to S. <hi>Andrews.</hi> and in particular let them bee carefull over the ſtudients in Colledges, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uo ſemel eſt imbuta recens ſervabit odorem teſta diu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for thoſe, who like the men of Succoth, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Meroz,</hi> refuſed to joyne with you, its well that you did not take the <hi>th rnes of the wilderneſſe, and bryers to teach them,</hi> to beat downe their houſes, this may content them, albeit you reſtore not their goods, which you tooke while you plundered their houſes. Though they be buſie ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, yet you are not bound according to our rules, <hi>Nullus tenetur cum vitae peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tolet. lb. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>aut famae rem alterius reſtituere, ſunt enim vita &amp; fama nobili oris ordinis quam res.</hi> No man is bound 01 with the danger of his life or good name to reſtore another man his goods againe, for life and a good name are of a more
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:112413:33"/>noble order then goods are: for albeit there be no danger of your life to reſtore every man his owne, yet your name is not ſafe, for if you reſtore to each man his goods againe, at leaſt it will be a <hi>tacite</hi> acknowledging of your robberie, and that is hurt ſome to a good name. But ſome ſay, that it is a matter of conſcience, to reſtore a mans goods againe, which is better then a good name, yea the way to recover a good name: but I refer this to the ſchooles.</p>
            <p>I have ſome matter of expoſtulation with you, but I will be loth to do it now, who have begun to congratulate with you for that ſweet <hi>Harmonie</hi> both in <hi>opinions</hi> and <hi>reaſons</hi> which is of late grown up amongſt us. Rome was not builded in one day, we muſt not look that at the firſt you can receive all our doctrine, though in a ſhort time you have profited much. <hi>Et vos converſi convertite fratres.</hi> Maſter <hi>Cant</hi> could preach at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> in what need England and Ireland ſtandeth of the Covenant, <hi>where ſome have their eares cut for the defence of the truth, and are groaning under the tyrannie of the whore of Babel.</hi> And ſince ſo it is, you ſhould pitie the blindneſſe of thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who have not a learned man in England or Ireland to lead them, but the blind leadeth the blind; But I perceive you are not negligent herein, your Ironicall preterition is moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, while you ſay,<note place="margin">Anſwer to the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>queſſe of <hi>Hamiltons</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</note> 
               <hi>We do not meddle with the Kirks of England or Ireland, but recommend to them the patterne ſhowne on the Mount.</hi> But what patterne of the mount is this I pray you? is it the Patterne ſhowne by you on <hi>Dunce hill,</hi> called by your preachers <hi>mount Sion,</hi> with an armie againſt the face of your King? if it be ſo, its a worthie patterne that requireth imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. But if the Patterne on the mount, be the <hi>Patterne of your diſcipline,</hi> you doe well herein, to imitate your progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: for they were deſirous to have <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> throwne downe in England as you are now, or as wee are deſirous; for their pride is ſo great, that the leaſt of them ſayes, that they have no more dependance from the Pope, then he from them: that their calling and place is of as great <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authoritie,</hi> as his is within his <hi>dioceſſe,</hi> thus limitating the <hi>univerſall</hi> Biſhop, as if hee were onely a <hi>Dioceſian.</hi> Yea they are not aſhamed to ſay, that all the Popiſh biſhops are but <hi>equivocally</hi> called Biſhops, and <hi>univocally</hi> are the Popes
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:112413:34"/>ſlaves: for as they have their power and authority from the Pope, ſo are they tyed to his obedience by oath. <hi>Romans pentifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci veram obedientiam ſpondeo acjuro.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Form. Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Bulla Pii <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> I promiſe and ſweare to give true obedience to the Pope of Rome. So that as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Apulia</hi> ſaid, ſo (ſay they) muſt all popiſh Biſhops ſay, <hi>Nos nihil aliud ſumus praeterqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> creatura &amp; mancipia pontificis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Carol Molm. conſil. ſape. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d. n. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> Wee are no other thing but the creatures and ſlaves of the Pope. And ſince the Pope will be only univerſall Biſhop, and all the reſt depending on him, as their head, they tell our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in the words of <hi>Gregory. Si unus univerſalis eſt, reſtatut vos epiſcopi non ſatis.</hi> If there be one univerſall Biſhop, it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that you are no Biſhops.<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. lib. <hi>7.</hi> ep. <hi>70.</hi>
               </note> Therefore I ſay, ſeeing your Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are greater enemies to our Hierarchie, then your ſelves are; you ſhall want no help that we can afford, to have them removed. I have ſeen your <hi>Gibſons</hi> letter to <hi>Coppinger, Hackets</hi> fellow labourer in England: Where he ſaies, <hi>The beſt of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are moſt carefull of your eſtate, and had ſent for that effect, a Preacher of our Church this laſt Summer</hi> (1590) <hi>of purpoſe to confer with the beſt afflicted miniſters of your Church, to lay down</hi> a plot, <hi>how our Church might best travell for your reliefe.</hi> But you do as well to ſend libels and informations, as to goe in your own perſons.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed any further either in my congratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or exhortation, I muſt relate unto you what I heard of that Anticovenanter, of whom I ſpake lately, when he read, <hi>That you</hi> did recommend to the Church of England and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>the pattern on the mount.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>This (ſayes he) brings to my remembrance a prettie Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie written by <hi>Melancthon. Vulpecula cauda amiſſa, reliquis vul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibus callidè perſuaſit, ut ſimiliter &amp; ipſae caudas reſecarent, ne ſola turpis &amp; deformis in ſuo genere videretur.</hi> A fox having loſt her taile, craftely perſwaded the other foxes, that they would likewiſe cut off their tailes, leſt ſhe her ſelfe alone, ſhould ſeem the foul and deformed beaſt of al that kind. Thus is their caſe who recommend their pattern to others. But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, while they thus labour to remove <hi>epiſcopacy,</hi> as unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſet up a <hi>new diſcipline</hi> as the only lawfull, in Chriſts Church, they do differ as much from their firſt Reformers, as wiſemen do from mad-men. For it is certaine, that even
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:112413:34"/>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> who firſt invented this diſcipline, did it not becauſe he judged <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> antichriſtian, or unlawfull, much leſſe did he recommend <hi>his diſcipline</hi> as a pattern to others: but it was only meere neceſſity which moved him, for if thoſe who were biſhops at the <hi>Reformation</hi> would have forſaken the Pope <hi>as their head,</hi> and embraced the <hi>reformed Religion,</hi> their <hi>calling</hi> had never beene called in queſtion, as appeareth by the words of <hi>Calvin</hi> to Cardinall <hi>Sadolete. Talem nobis hierarchiam ſi exhibeant, in qua ſic emineant Epiſcopi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Calvin. epiſt. ad Card. Sadolet.</note> 
                  <hi>ut Chriſto ſubeſſe non recuſent ut ab illo tanquam unico capite pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deant, &amp; ad ipſum referantur: in qua ſic inter ſe fraternam ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietatem colant, ut von alio modo, quam ejus veritati ſint colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gati, tum vero, nullo non anathemate dignos fatear, ſi qui erunt, qui non cum reverenter, ſumma<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> obedientia obſervent.</hi> If they doe bring unto us ſuch an <hi>Hierarchie,</hi> wherein the Biſhops ſhall ſo be preferred, that they refuſe not to ſubmit themſelves to Chriſt, that they alſo depend upon him as their onely head, and have their relation to him, in which Hierarchie they may ſo keepe brotherly ſocietie among themſelves, that they bee not other wayes knit together, but by his truth: then ſurely if there ſhall be any, that ſhall not ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to that <hi>Hierarchie reverently,</hi> and with the greateſt <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> that may bee, I confeſſe there is no kinde of curſe whereof they are not worthie. A fore ſentence for a covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Beza</hi> likewiſe himſelfe hearing that ſome did offend at the <hi>innovation of diſcipline</hi> (which neceſſity put upon them) and thought that he and his colleagues did ſet out the ſame as a patterne for other Churches, to follow, was not a little diſpleaſed, and told that it was never their intention to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe ſuch a diſcipline, where the old might be kept, hee wiſheth them to keepe it ſtill.<note place="margin">Beza de g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad. miniſt. cap. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Frnantur igitur illo quivolent &amp; poterunt.</hi> Therefore let them enjoy Epiſcopal government who deſire and may do it: and ſayes in that ſame place, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit ut tune ordinem temerè aut ſuperbé reprehendam.</hi> God forbid that I ſhould raſhly or proudly reprove that order, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the 21. chap. of the cited booke, having ſpoken of the tyranny of the <hi>Popiſh Biſhops</hi> did hinder the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he tels us, that he doth neither mean <hi>Proteſtant Biſhops,</hi> nor yet ſet forth their diſcipline, as a <hi>Pattern</hi> to be followed.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:112413:35"/>
                  <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tamen nujus tyrannidis omnes archiepiſcopes, ſen epiſcopes hodie vocatos accuſamus: quae fuerit enim haec arrogantia? i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ò cunctos, ſic hodie appellatos (modo ſanctiſſimorum illoruns E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporum exemplum imitentur, &amp; tam miſere deformatam d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Dei, ex verbi divini regula inſtaurent) ut eccleſia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anae ſidos paſtores, cur non agnoſcamus, &amp; omni reverentia proſequamur? nedum ut (quod falſiſſimè &amp; impudentiſſime aonnulli nobis objiciunt) cuipiam uſsiam eccleſiae ſepuenduns noſtrum peculiare exemplum praeſcribamus.</hi> And yet wee doe not accuſe all, that are this day called Archbiſhops or Biſhops, of this tyrannie: for what arrogancie were that? yea, why ſhould wee not acknowledge, and honour with all reverence, all that are this day ſo called, as the faithfull paſtors of the Chriſtian Church: ſo being they would imitate the example of thoſe moſt holy Biſhops in the primitive Church, and reform by the rule of Gods word the deformed houſe of God? much leſſe that we ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to any Church in any place, <hi>our peculiar example to be followed,</hi> which moſt falſly, and moſt ſhameleſly ſome object unto us. So the authors of the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> Confeſſion declare ingeniouſly, that it was not any diſlike at <hi>Epiſcopall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtan. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> but the crueltie of <hi>Popiſh Biſhops,</hi> who did by all means hinder the reformation of Religion, which did diſſolve that government and Canonicall policie, <hi>quam magnopere cupie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamus conſervare,</hi> which we earneſtly deſired to preſerve. And therefore, ſeeing <hi>popiſh Biſhops</hi> were in place then, and <hi>Proteſtant Biſhops</hi> could not be ſet in their place, they decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the world in their confeſſion, that (notwithſtanding it was removed) they did approve it, and were ſo free from having the fault imputed to them, that it did not remaine among them; that they were moſt willing it ſhould bee continued, if thoſe <hi>Popiſh Biſhops</hi> would forbeare their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and turne <hi>Proteſtans,</hi> and ſtudie to advance the <hi>Reformation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> For they ſay, <hi>Hiciterum teſtatum volumus, nos libentur conſervaturos eſſe eccleſiaſticam &amp; canonicam poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, ſi modo Epiſcopi deſinant in noſtras Eccleſias ſavire, Haec noſtra voluntas, &amp; coram Deo, &amp; apud omnes gentes ad omnem poſteritatem excuſabit nos, ne nobis imputari poſſit, quod epiſcoporum authoritas labefactetur.</hi> Here againe, wee
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:112413:35"/>will have it teſtified, that we ſhall willingly keep ſtill the Eccleſiaſticall and Canonicall policy, if ſo be the Biſhops will forbeare to rage againſt our Churches. This is our will, and it ſhall excuſe us before God, among all Nations to all poſterity, that it cannot be imputed to us, that the authority of Biſhops is decayed.<note place="margin">Ibid de potest. Eccleſ.</note> And againe, in that ſame confeſſion they ſay, <hi>Saepe jam teſtati ſumus, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> von ſolùm poteſtatem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticam quae in Evangelio inſtituta eſt, ſummâ pietate ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerari, ſed etiam Eccleſiaſticam politiam, &amp; gradus in Eccleſia magnopere probare, &amp; quantum in nobis eſt conſervare cupere: non detractamus authoritatem Epiſcoporum, modò non cogant facere contra mandatum Dei. Hac votuntas liberabit nos coram Deo, &amp; judicio univerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> poſteritatis, né j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dicomur re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hujus ſchiſmatis, quod initio excitatum est injuſtâ damnatione doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Lutheri.</hi> We have already oftimes teſtified, that we, not onely with the greateſt piety that can be, do reverence that Eccleſiaſticall power inſtituted in the Goſpell, but alſo do very much approve the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall policie, and degrees in the Church,</hi> and deſire to keep it, as much as we can: We do not refuſe the <hi>authority</hi> of Biſhops, if ſo be they doe not compell us to do againſt the Command of God. This our will ſhall deliver us before God, and in the judgement of all our poſterity, that wee bee not judged guilty of that <hi>Schiſme,</hi> which at the beginning was raiſed by the unjuſt condemning of the Doctrine of <hi>Luther.</hi> O how farre do thoſe Covenanters differ from thoſe Reformers! How can they cleare themſelves before God, the Reformed Churches, and the ages to come, who have made this <hi>great Schiſme?</hi> They not onely have <hi>condemned,</hi> that which all reformed Churches do <hi>commend,</hi> but alſo ſtudy to hatch the cockatrice egge, and bring forth ſerpents, <hi>Schiſmes</hi> and <hi>Rebellions</hi> in other calme Churches, who live at peace. Looke now farre theſe Reformers did tender <hi>Epiſcopacio,</hi> as much do theſe Covenanters hate it: It is not ſufficient to them, to have thruſt from them without any cauſe their Biſhops, (except it be that the Biſhops have carried themſelves to them, as <hi>David</hi> did to <hi>Adonijah.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>And his father did not diſpleaſe him at any time, in ſaying, Why haſt thou done ſo?</hi> by which too gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle dealing, they gave them occaſion to riſe up againſt them)
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:112413:36"/>but they themſelves muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, buſie Biſhops in another mans Dioceſſe; yea, be <hi>univerſall Biſhops,</hi> within the Kings Dominions, by their ſeuſleſſe (yet malicious) libels and letters, to his Majeſties good Subjects in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> labouring to produce the like <hi>Diſorders</hi> among them, that they ſhould not remaine alone filthy and deformed in the Church of God. Howbeit, all good and learned men (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven among thoſe, who have not <hi>Epiſcopall government</hi>) doe declare their dutifull and reverent reſpects to Biſhops; yet, for the accompliſhing of their bad ends, it hath beene their chief labour, firſt and laſt, to make Biſhops moſt odious and contemptible to all men.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Thus <hi>Cant</hi> at <hi>Glaſgow</hi> in his Sermon (becauſe the Biſhop of <hi>Glaſgow</hi> did dwell in the Caſtle, neare to the Cathedrall Church) told the people, that <hi>Satan had his dwelling among them, and Antichriſt had a neſt among them: and cried, pull downe, pull downe Antichriſts neſt,</hi> with many other expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, more worthy of the <hi>ſpeaker;</hi> than of the <hi>Hearers;</hi> there wanted nothing to draw the multitude to the perpetrating of a miſchief againſt that old reverend Father, but that God ſuffered not any to be a head to the furious multitude.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Thus they have too obſequiouſly obſerved the direction of their book entituled,<note place="margin">Sions Plea, pag. 196.</note> 
                  <hi>Sions Plea:</hi> Where it's ſaid, <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Magiſtrates maſt labour, and cauſe others to labour for an holy hatred of Prelates, and their brethren, with an holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, to daſh the braines of the Babyloniſh Prelacie againſt the ſtones.</hi> And according <hi>to Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>But thoſe mine enemies, that would not that J ſhould raigne over them, bring hither, and ſlay them before me. And ſtrike that Hazael in the fifth rib, yea, if father or mother ſtand in the way, away with them. Strike the Baſiliske veine, for nothing but this will cure the plurifie of this our ſtate.</hi> This is a notable policie, and as well learned by the Covenanters, as taught by their maſters, and have made ſuch proficiencie herein, that they ſtand in more need of a <hi>bridle,</hi> than of a <hi>ſpurre;</hi> they have by lies and calumnies with the changeable multitude ſo prevailed, that they have not ſo much as any being among them, but as they ſay, <hi>Have ſwept the dirt and duſt out of Gods houſe, and ſent them to the land of Nod.</hi> But yet, Thanks be to God, notwithſtanding of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:112413:36"/>their throwing ſtone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at them, they have not daſht their braines againſt the ſtones, and for <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ael<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> fift rib, they have onely ſmote a Biſhops coach-horſe. And as for this <hi>Baſiliske veine,</hi> which they would have ſtriken, it's of a higher na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, than the killing of Biſhops; for it's borrowed from the Ieſuites, who by that phraſe, underſtand the killing of Kings and Princes: Wherefore one of them ſaid, <hi>Erratum valac fuiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in fiſto Bartholomai,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Carol. Scrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</note> 
                  <hi>quòd ſcci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rit vena Baſilica, id eſt, quòd parcitum fuit regi Navarra, &amp; principi Condenſi.</hi> It was a great ſault, that in the feaſt of <hi>Bartholomew</hi> the Baſiliske veine was not ſtriken, that is to ſay, that the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was let alone. But they have done as much as they can, to ſtrike at this Baſiliske veine through the Biſhops ſides. For I remember, when at the beginning of theſe diſorders many did ask, why they did make the Biſhops their adverſaries, and complaine upon them, ſince they did never require any thing, but by warrant of his Majeſties authority, whom they ought to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey; it was uſually anſwered, <hi>Some man muſt be whipped, and rather the Biſhops, than any.</hi> God knowes how foule a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter this might ſuffer. And as for thoſe calumnies, filthy ballads, which theſe men ſet out to the diſgrace of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, rather than of thoſe whom they hate; they deſerve no other anſwer, than that of the Prophet. <hi>The vile perſon will ſpeake villany, and his heart will worke iniquity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.6.</note> 
                  <hi>to practiſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and to utter errour againſt the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> And in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, this ſentence doth juſty appertaine to that vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Alexander Sempill,</hi> who for whoredome, drunkenneſſe, and all kinde of Licentiouſneſſe, hath not a ſecond in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and now by meanes of whoriſh Women,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>is brought to a piece of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ead,</hi> and extreme poverty, having nothing left but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit body, an intoxicate braine, and railing tongue: ſo that I wonder, who could be ſo baſe, as to lend him their hand to write for him that fooliſh, (but ſeditious) ballad, called the <hi>Biſhops bridles.</hi> And I marvell more, that the Covenanters have made this <hi>pattern of wickedneſſe,</hi> to be their fitteſt man to preſent to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> their <hi>partern on the Mount:</hi> for they print nothing there now without the approbation of one <hi>Johnſon,</hi> Clerke of their aſſemblies.<note place="margin">So he prints himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> This <hi>AS</hi> or
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:112413:37"/>
                  <hi>Alexander Sempill</hi> is ſo beaſtly and apiſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that he can finde no other <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>ſubject</hi> for his ballad, but to allude to one <hi>Rew</hi>'s preaching on <hi>Balaams</hi> aſſe, which they make to be the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that have thrown off the Biſhops, their riders: and therefore muſt ſell their bridles. This Preacher <hi>Rew,</hi> did not put ſhame enough upon that Church, but this <hi>AS</hi> muſt ſecond him, and continue its ſhame. That of the Wiſeman is fit for them, <hi>A whip for the horſe, a bridle for the Aſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 26.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and a rod for the fooles back.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>But ſince they delight in this compariſon, and will have their Church to be an Aſſe, and the Biſhops their riders; I ſhall not diſpleaſe them ſo to call it. But let them remember that the Biſhops rode upon this Aſſe meekly, dealing with them,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.21.</note> 
                  <hi>not with the rod, but in love, with the ſpirit of meekneſse.</hi> But the Lay-Biſhops have throwne them off, and now ride ſo <hi>furiouſly</hi> like <hi>Jehu,</hi> that we complaine with the Pſalmiſt.<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 66.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt cauſed men to ride over our heads, we went through fire and water:</hi> they<note n="b" place="margin">2 King 4.24.</note> 
                  <hi>drive and go forward, and ſlacke not their riding:</hi> they ſtudy to make her <hi>a wilde</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 2.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Aſse uſed to the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse, that ſnuffeth up the Wind at her pleaſure,</hi> and is ſo farre drawne away in the wilderneſſe, that his Majeſty hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more paines to finde her out, and bring her from her wandering,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 9.3.</note> than <hi>Saul</hi> did in <hi>ſeeking his fathers aſses,</hi> he ſought his Fathers aſſes but three dayes, but his Majeſty hath ſought this aſſe three yeares. There is no queſtion but ſhe would be found and returne,<note place="margin">Eſa. 1.3.</note> for the <hi>aſse knowes her Maſters crib:</hi> but her riders will not ſuffer her, perſwading her that his Majeſty will miſcrably handle her: though they aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know themſelves, that his Majeſty will do no more harm to her, than the Lion did to the aſſe, whereon the ſeduced Prophet rode,<note place="margin">1 King. 13.28.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lion did not teare the Aſse,</hi> the Scripture ſayes, but killed the ſeduced rider. This is the onely feare they have, not for the aſſe, but for the riders, who have juſtly provoked the <hi>Lions wrath, as the meſsenger of death;</hi> and to be <hi>buried with the buriall of an aſse,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 22.19.</note> 
                  <hi>drawn and caſt forth beyond the gates of Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </q> Here the Anticovenanter would have proceeded, but I not being deſirous to trouble my ſelfe in diſpute with him, cut him off with your words. The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters are exhorted not <hi>to be moved with remonſtrances, were
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:112413:37"/>they never ſo ſpecious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but ſubmit themſelves obediently to follow their leaders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenanters i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>form for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive. §. 4.</note> 
               <hi>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m God at this time hath largely furuiſhed with courage and counſell, for the good of his Kirke and Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me.</hi> But he anſwered me, <hi>The leaders of this people cauſe them to erre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>and they that are led of them, are deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaving him, I returne to my exhortation. If you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perſwade men to <hi>your pitte ne on the mount,</hi> at leaſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to poſſeſſe them with the opinions and doctrines, which you have received of us. I ſpecially his is the duty of <hi>Blair</hi> and <hi>Livingſton,</hi> to water the good ſeed which they have ſown in ſome of the hearts of ſome of your countrey-men in the North part of Ireland: and by their frequent exhortations and letters, to perſwade them to grow, and be fruitfull in thoſe matters. Eſpecially let them, by <hi>fearefull threatings</hi> of Gods judgements, aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight them from taking that <hi>unl wfull oath</hi> which eſtabliſheth the Kings <hi>Supremacie,</hi> and is urged by my <hi>Lord Deputy,</hi> (to whom, I confeſſe, his Maſters honour is more deare, than the Apple of his eye) ſo <hi>violently,</hi> that he will ſuffer no man to vilipend it, but will have them ſweare ſuch an oath, that they ſhall never <hi>tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their King, nor proteſt againſt him, but to obey his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all commands.</hi> Whereby thus violently he hath put your cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant out of credit among the Scots there, except you provide ſome remedy.</p>
            <p>I heare that not only <hi>Blair</hi> and <hi>Livingſton,</hi> but that <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torfort,</hi> and <hi>Dickson</hi> alſo, have lent their helping hand, and have written a learned refutation of that <hi>Oath</hi> to be taken by the Scots there. I am ſorry that I did not ſee it, that I might have increaſed my congratulati n. Did you ever ſee the two <hi>Apoſtolike brieft,</hi> which our holy Father <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aulu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 5. ſent to the Catholikes in England, that were urged with the <hi>ſame Oath,</hi> that is preſſed upon your brethren now? Or did you ever read <hi>Bellarmines</hi> letter to <hi>Blakwell?</hi> if you did, they have helped you well in that matter, I am ſure. <hi>Becanus</hi> tels us the ſumme of all which the Pope and Cardinall did write. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terque negat ſalvâ conſcientiâ praeſtari poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bec m. diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id. Angl.</note> 
               <hi>hoc juramentum à rege propoſitum, quia abnegarent ſidem Catholicam.</hi> They both deny, that that oath preſcribed by the King, can be taken with a ſafe conſcience, becauſe they would deny the Catholike
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:112413:38"/>Faith. They ſay, you ſay the ſame, onely you add many fearfull judgements upon both the <hi>exacter</hi> and <hi>takers</hi> of the ſame. And therefore you may ſay of them that take this oath,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> as <hi>Becanus</hi> doth, <hi>Hoc faciunt ad extremam patem &amp; politiam conſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, quae pluris abillis quam fides &amp; religio aſtimatur, ideóque politici poti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s quàm Chriſtiani appellandi ſunt.</hi> They do this that they may preſerve outward peace, which they eſteeme more than of Faith and Religion; and therefore they ought rather to be called <hi>Politicians</hi> than <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſut. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> p. <hi>1</hi> para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> For no man will grant the Kings <hi>Supremacy, excepto Sacellano, &amp; quibuſdam aliis adulatoribus regiis.</hi> Except the Kings Chaplaine, (Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren es</hi>) and ſome other <hi>Court Paraſites.</hi> And here by the way I muſt tell you a notable untruth of that <hi>Biſhop Andrewes,</hi> in his diſpute againſt <hi>Bellarmine:</hi> he holds that the <hi>Puritans</hi> do willingly take the oath of <hi>Supremacy.</hi> But albeit he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, having five tongues, yet with none of his five tongues could he ſpeake true in this, as our <hi>Becanus</hi> proveth from no leſſe than the teſtimony of his owne Maſter K. <hi>Iames,</hi> in his <hi>Baſil. Doron.</hi> But I finde one <hi>Richardus Thomſonus in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencho refutationis Torturae torti,</hi> defending <hi>Andrewes,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling him with his maſter, by telling, that the King ſpake of Scots <hi>Puritans;</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Engliſh Puritans.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this may ſatisfie or not, I leave it to a farther inquirie.</p>
            <p>If the for lorne brother of our ſociety <hi>Abernethie</hi> hath done our Church any ſervice among you, in the farthering and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving this your happy <hi>return</hi> to us; he hath ſowell deſerved, that there is hope for him to be received of us againe. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit his crimes were ſo ugly, that we did exclude him from our Church and orders;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2 6.</note> yet <hi>ſufficient to this man is the puniſhment inflicted upon him by many.</hi> For he hath reconciled himſelfe (as the people of <hi>Gath</hi> feared <hi>David</hi> would do) with your <hi>heads</hi> and <hi>hearts:</hi> in enlightening your braine with the knowledge, &amp; your hearts with the love of many principall points of our doctrine.<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.17.</note> Exhort him to continue unto the end. <hi>I endeavoured my ſelfe to have come unto you, I deſired to ſee you earneſtly, and would have come unto you once and againe, but Satan hindered me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though in this my <hi>Congratulatorie Epiſtle,</hi> I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times inſerted my <hi>counſell</hi> and <hi>exhortation</hi> unto you, let not this diſpleaſe you, as if I thought you deficient herein, or
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:112413:38"/>that you had need of ſpurs, who run with born-down-head. For all my exhortations are nothing elſe, but a pleaſant repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of your doings, and a ſympathizing expreſſion of our conjunct approbation thereof. So that my <hi>recommendation</hi> of that to your practiſe, which you are doing, is ſo farre from inſimulating you of negligence, that it is rather a <hi>commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of your actions, according to that of the Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui menet ut facias, quod jam facis, ipſe monendo</l>
               <l>Laudat; &amp; hortatu c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mprobat ipſe ſuo.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Salute all our friends, and eſpecially at your night-meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for devotion, ſalute the ſiſters with a holy kiſſe. To whom you doe but your duty when you acknowledge your cauſe much obliged unto them, and that in thoſe your <hi>Eſthers</hi> and <hi>Judiths</hi> your work had but a ſmall beginning: and when men durſt not reſiſt the beginnings, it's wiſely obſerved by you, that <hi>God moved the ſpirit of thoſe holy women to ſcourge the buyers and ſellers out of Gods houſe, and not to ſuffer the ſame to be polluted with that foule Booke of Common Prayer.</hi> Thoſe holy Matrons who waſt themſelves with <hi>Faſting,</hi> have deſerved ſo well at your hands, that you ſhould exhort them, (as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Timothy</hi>) <hi>to take a little wine to comfort them:</hi> and to incourage them to proceed zealouſly in your cauſe, for they are the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er veſſels, and wine will ſtrengthen them. Read 1 <hi>Eſdras</hi> chap. 3. ver. 21. Where it is ſaid thus. <hi>Wine is exceeding ſtrong, it makes every heart rich, ſo that a man remembreth neither King nor Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, and it maketh to ſpeak all things by talents. And when they are in their cups, they forget their love both to friends and brethren, and a little after draw out ſwords,</hi> &amp;c. Albeit this be a paſſage out of <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> yet your practiſe ſayes it is not falſe.</p>
            <p>Our women here carie a ſiniſtrous opinion of your women, whom they call <hi>virago's</hi> and <hi>monſters</hi> of women, a diſgrace to their ſex, man-like-women, and a new kind of <hi>Hermaphrodits;</hi> becauſe of their violent and turbulent carriage (as they call it) in abuſing all men that are contrary minded, they ſay,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Non metuunt leges, ſed cedit viribus aequum,</l>
               <l>Quámque lupi ſaevae plus firitutis habent.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That is, they feare no Lawes, but equity giveth place to force, and they have more ſavage cruelty in them than the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Wolves. But our Ladies are miſtaken, not knowing that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:112413:39"/>this proceeds from Zeal. <hi>Impetus hic, ſacrae ſemina mentis babet.</hi> This violence of theirs hath the feeds of a holy minde: And they being free citizens, ought to have full freedome: their tongues are their owne, what Lord can them controll? If <hi>Tyberius</hi> when he was railed upon in the city, tooke it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, ſaying, <hi>In libera cevitate oportet linguam eſſe liberam.</hi> Why ſhould not <hi>free Subjects</hi> in a <hi>free</hi> kingdome, have <hi>free</hi> tongues, and <hi>free</hi> hands too? eſpecially of <hi>Women,</hi> when reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is in queſtion. <hi>Gutlielmus Poſtellus</hi> ſet out a book, which he entituled: <hi>Of the victory of women.</hi> I would have the like done by ſome of you, eſpecially by him, who gave his ghoſtly bleſſing to thoſe <hi>manfull</hi> women (who ſhew their valour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their adverſaries, in beating them and their books out of Gods houſe) <hi>My bleſſing light upon you all my deare Bird all.</hi> Break not off your nocturnall devotions, and aſſembling together for the better, and not for the worſe. But doe it more ſecretly than <hi>Andrew Leſley,</hi> of whom they ſay, that hee forſooke <hi>Ireland</hi> to go to the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the firſt fruits whereof was, to forſake <hi>his wife,</hi> to joyne himſelfe with <hi>an harlot.</hi> The good old Matron of the holy Siſters of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> did more cunningly cover her daughters infirmity of the fleſh,<note place="margin">R. A.</note> who (as ſhe ſaid to her ſiſters at their meetings) had fallen in a <hi>holy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> with a brother, not out of <hi>Luſt,</hi> but <hi>Love:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore decreed, that ſhe ſhould not confeſſe it before the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, leſt the <hi>Goſpell ſhould be ſcandalized, and that it was better to fall in the hands of God, by ſwearing that ſhe did not know the man, than to fall in the hands of men, by confeſſing her carnall fact.</hi> We ſay well to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t liv. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mentiri in confeſſion, non ſemper eſt peccatum mortale.</hi> To lie in confeſſion, is not ever a mortall ſin: but it was a pitie, that ſhortly after ſhe had ſworne, her ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling belly belied her; and yet, here the <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>ſcandall</hi> of your devout profeſſion was more than your ſin; for that kind of ſin is but a <hi>weakneſſe</hi> and <hi>infirmity,</hi> and if it be acted for <hi>good ends</hi> and <hi>intentions,</hi> it is no ſin at all. Therfore, it's well ſaid by a father of our Society. <hi>Si quis pollutionem deſideraret ob bonum finem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I lem lib. cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſcilicet ſanitatem, vel ad levandas tentationes quibus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu aſſlig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur, non eſt peccatum.</hi> If any deſire, &amp;c. for a good end, to wit, for <hi>their health;</hi> or to put away the <hi>tentations,</hi> wherewith they are troubled all the day long, it's
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:112413:39"/>not a ſin. And therefore it's thought, when thoſe holy Siſters are longeſt out at their night-devotions, they are much amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their health the next day. And we do alſo hold,<note n="*" place="margin">De judicili l. <hi>2.</hi> Decret. <hi>6</hi> Cap. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Et Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ici.</note> 
               <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terium inter minora, crimina cenſendum eſſe,</hi> That Adulterie is to be eſteemed among the ſmaller crimes;<note n="†" place="margin">Cauſ. <hi>31.</hi> qv. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. Hac ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; eſſe aliquam hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtam fornicationem.</hi> and that there is ſome <hi>honeſt fornication.</hi> Or (as that Matron called it) <hi>holy fornication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is very ominous which I heare, that many huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands will not ſuffer their wives to frequent thoſe night-mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings as they were wont to do. That is a fearefull preſage, that that <hi>order</hi> and <hi>ſocietie</hi> ſhall be cryed down, except they get it confirmed by aſſembly. For we had a Societie of Siſters cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Congregatio Ieſuitiſſarum,</hi> ſuppreſſed by our holy Father Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> the 8. anno 1631. <hi>Quia novum ordir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m inſtituerunt aſſumpto Jeſuitiſſarum nomine,</hi>—<hi>qua per multa opera ſexus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bulla V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ban. Papae <hi>8.</hi> Roma edita. <hi>1631.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genii imbecillitati, &amp; modeſtiae muliebri, virginali preſertim pudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri minimè comementia, attentarunt &amp; exercuerunt.</hi> Becauſe they did inſtitute a new order, aſſuming the name of Ieſuitiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who have attempted and exerciſed many works, which do not become the weaknes of their ſex and ingenie, nor the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie of women, and eſpecially moſt unbeſeeming virginall ſhamefaſtnes. The like caſe may befall your ſocietie, if it be not prevented; if your <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kie</hi> and his <hi>Collegues</hi> be not authorized, it's to be feared that the ſocietie of thoſe Siſters ſhall get a down-fall.</p>
            <p>I have heard of the great controverſie betweene him and ſome miniſters of <hi>Sterling ſhire,</hi> and that the matter was deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in your aſſemblie, but what was done, I was not fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; only I heard of your moderation, that you thought it not fit, to diſcharge his new <hi>ſocietie</hi> by <hi>act</hi> of aſſembly, but by way of <hi>counſell,</hi> but he rejects your counſell, and though hee hath not an <hi>ordinary calling,</hi> yet he tels that he hath an <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary calling</hi> from God, and bids you, <hi>behold it in the fruits of his labours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am moſt of all affraid for our ſelvs, though we have an ordinary calling and authority for our <hi>order.</hi> We are ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both by friend and foe, at home and abroad, that wee are daily perplexed, eſpecially ſince the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dnulling of the <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſſaes</hi> order: upon which ſome Poet (by way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:112413:40"/>as is thought) made thoſe verſes, with a <hi>fiat.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Foemineus ſexus ſociis immixtus Ieſu</l>
               <l>Tranſcendit ſexus munia foeminci.</l>
               <l>Non tulit hanc labem <hi>VRBANI</hi> vigilantia Papae,</l>
               <l>Suppreſſit Socias, mox Socioſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> premet.</l>
            </q>
            <p>We have ſuffered already great hurt in divers places, being hunted to and fro, as if we were Malefactors. And I doubt not but you know how weake we are in <hi>France,</hi> we dare not deny the King of <hi>France</hi> his <hi>Supremacie,</hi> and muſt acknowledge his Dominion to be independent, in reſpect of men, and that the King holds his Kingdome by vertue of,<note place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>Per me reges regnant, by me Kings raigne.</hi> The Doctors of the Vniverſity of <hi>Paris have done us much evill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord reward them according to their workes.</hi> They have condemned ſome of the workes of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Becanus</hi> in their Vniverſities, and have publiſhed the ſame to the world, whether the Pope would or no; and are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo become <hi>Court-Paraſites.</hi> And their chiefe labour is by their doctrine in contradiction to you and us, to corrupt all eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Noblemens children, that come to their Vniverſities: and at leaſt once a yeare, make every one of them under their hands, to profeſſe the Kings independent power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Therefore now our holy <hi>League</hi> is wholly dead, <hi>and death feeds upon it in the grave,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.14.</note> and we are become vile, and herein are turned <hi>Saduceans,</hi> to deny the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of our holy <hi>League,</hi> or any ſuch <hi>inſurrection,</hi> ſo long as ſuch doctors (as the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi>) ſhall thus infect the land, and make noble and ignoble ſuch Court Paraſites. But your caſe is far better than ours at this time: for you have put away from your Vniverſities ſuch as withſtood you, and have placed ſuch men in your Vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Glaſgow</hi> and S. <hi>Andrewes</hi> and <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> who will cauſe the ſchollers to drink ſuch a full draught of our doctrine, that they ſhall vomit out all which your adverſaries taught them. We are not ſo happie, our enemies prevaile daily againſt us. But yours are dying, eſpecially the Archbiſhop of S. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes,</hi> to whom we wiſhed no better death, nor more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable buriall, then that Martyr and brother of our Societie <hi>Iohn Ogleby</hi> got, whom he cauſed to be hanged at the Croſſe of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> becauſe he ſtood to the defence of our doctrine, which he brought within the compaſſe of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> by the lawes of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:112413:40"/>your kingdom, which I pray you to abrogate. D. <hi>Baron</hi> that great enemy of ours, is alſo dead (as they ſay) in perſecution. At this we do both rejoyce, as if we had found a great ſpoyle.</p>
            <p>We had alſo great credit (according to our hearts deſire) at <hi>Conſtaminople</hi> and among the <hi>Galathians,</hi> and divers parts in the Eaſt, but by the meanes of the King of great Brittane, &amp;c. his ambaſſador, and <hi>Cyrillus</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> (who is of the Religion of the Church of England, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims the Popes juriſdiction, even as the Biſhops of England do) We are all baniſhed the Turks bounds, and a Shipfull of us was ſent home to <hi>Italy</hi> from <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> Since wee cannot get libertie to remain in the Eaſt, we purpoſe to come to you in the Weſt, where there is neither Patriarch nor Biſhop to trouble us, as <hi>Cyrillus</hi> did at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if King <hi>Charles</hi> follow the direction of his Father King <hi>Iames</hi> our <hi>common enemie,</hi> your caſe will bee little better then ours was at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> For after he hath directed his ſon to beware of <hi>Puritans, as moſt peſtilent followes, both in Church and policie, whom neither the Kings favours and bountie,</hi> nor their own promiſes and oaths can make faithfull and loyall, but being <hi>above meaſure arrogant,</hi> they belch out nothing but <hi>calumnies and ſeditions,</hi> and contrary to the Word of God fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their owne <hi>dreames and conceits,</hi> as the only rule of their conſcience, he ſayes moſt pathetically.<note place="margin">Baſilic doron. pag. <hi>148</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Teſtor illum magnum Deum (nec teſtamentum condenti fas eſt mentiri) nunquam inter montanos aut limitancos noſtros latronos, majorem ingratitudinem, aut per fidiam reperiri poſse, quam inter hos phanaticos nebulones: nee paterec, ſi pacatè vivere decreveris, ut hi eadem tecum patria fruautur, niſi fortè patientiae experienda ergo, ut Socrates vixit cum Xanthippo.</hi> I take the great God to witneſſe, as if I were making my teſtament (and it is not lawfull for him that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a teſtament to lye) that there can never be more unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; or perfidiouſneſſe found among our High-land and bordering robbers, then among thoſe brain-ſicke villaines. Neither do thou ſuffer them to enjoy that ſame countrey with thee, if thou purpoſe to live peaceably, unleſſe perchance, for the exerciſe of thy patience, as <hi>Socrates</hi> lived with <hi>Xantippe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a dreadfull adviſe, and our caſe is ſo miſcrable, that it is our lot and deſtinie to be like <hi>Iſhmael the wild man, whoſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:112413:41"/>hands were againſt every man, and every mans hands againſt him.</hi> But let us not be diſmaied, not our hearts melt, nor our hands be faint;<note place="margin">Gen. 16.12.</note> but let us joyne hand in hand together, <hi>(Virtus unita fortior)</hi> And we ſhall ſpeake with the enemy in the gate. <hi>And the righteous ſhall be delivered out of trouble, and the wicked ſhall come in his ſtead, Prov.</hi> 11.8.</p>
            <p>I have many other things to write to you, which I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay til I have the opportunity to write a ſecond Epiſtle, which ſhall be, ſo ſoone as I heare what fruits this firſt Epiſtle ſhall produce: Which, I pray you cauſe to be printed among you for your common good, becauſe I could not get many copies ſent to you, being ſo far from you beyond ſea. If AS's <hi>Bridles</hi> was thought worthy to be printed by your authority, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Biſhops; why may not this my Epiſtle be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for the edification of your Societie. Let it not offend you that I have not railed in this my Epiſtle againſt authority in Church and policie: for our Society hath been ſo oft reproved for railing that I doe now begin to forbeare it, for the honour of our Order, neither will we permit infamous Paſquils lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to come forth, and it were good that you did ſo too, and let us ſpeak home to the purpoſe, convincing our adverſaries with evident reaſons; and make their errours and hereſies known to the world, rather then to vent our ſpleen againſt them with calumnies; This doth but open the mouth of our adverſaries; but that will ſtop it: this makes diſgrace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon our ſelves, but the other, makes us gracious. If we raile, when we ſhould reaſon, we get no anſwer, but <hi>increpet te Dominus.</hi> But when we reaſon, without railing; we beget in them <hi>diſsentiendi pudorem. &amp; veritatis timorem.</hi> A baſhfulnes to diſſent from us, and a reverence of the truth; which in time, will bring forth a profeſſion of it.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Farewell.</hi>
               <dateline>From my ſtudy at <hi>Baſileopolis</hi> 
                  <date>The firſt of Ianuary, 1640.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112413:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
